<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[German Brief]]></title><description><![CDATA[German Brief was conceived to report on, discuss and explain German affairs. It covers a broad range of topics that are of interest and consequence.]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/journal</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:04:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.germanbrief.com/blog-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[German weather in 2024]]></title><description><![CDATA[German weather in 2024: Record temperatures and rainfalls]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-weather-in-2024</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6773f37d20c3f052c34c5c21</guid><category><![CDATA[Environment]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 14:11:03 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">GERMAN WEATHER IN 2024</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Record temperatures and rainfall in 2024 caused catastrophic flooding in many parts of Germany</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_3928eff791544c58a9c0b0228f89c55c~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="German weather 2024"></figure>
<p>2024’s unusually high average temperatures and record rainfalls resulted in flooding and caused thunderstorms and gustnadoes (photo)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>January 2025: 2024 was the warmest year in Germany since records began in 1881. It was also significantly wetter than usual. According to the German Weather Service (Deutscher Wetterdienst DWD), the average temperature between January and December 2024 was 10.9 degrees. That was 2.7 degrees more than the average from 1961 to 1990 and 1.6 degrees more than from 1991 to 2020.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to evaluations by the DWD, some 903 litres per square metre of precipitation fell across the country in 2024. This is around 110 litres more than the average for the years 1961 to 2020, while the sun shone slightly less than usual at 1,507 hours.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Uwe Kirsche, DWD press spokesperson, said: “What is particularly alarming is that 2024 exceeded the previous year by an extraordinary 0.3 degrees. This is accelerated climate change.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The very mild winter of 2023/2024 and the record-breaking warm spring also brought unusually high precipitation levels. 2024 was a much wetter than usual year in Germany. The duration of sunshine was slightly above the typical average for this country.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The spring also went down in the DWD&apos;s climate statistics as the warmest since measurements began. The summer was also remarkably warm - August was even one of the four warmest since 1881. In September, heat records in the northeast set new standards, and the subsequent average autumn temperature, which was significantly too high, completed the character of the record-breaking warm year.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>2024 with some extremely wet periods of precipitation, high water and flooding’ According to evaluations by the DWD, a good 903 litres per square metre (l/m²) of precipitation fell in 2024. This was significantly more than the average for the reference periods of 1961 to 1990, with 789 l/m² and 1991 to 2020, with 791 l/m².</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The year began with winter flooding in Lower Saxony, North Rhine-Westphalia and Saxony-Anhalt. Winter and spring were particularly rainy, with the hydrological winter half-year (November 2023 to April 2024) being the wettest in Germany since measurements began. Over the year, the DWD measured the highest amounts on the edge of the Alps and in the Black Forest, with over 2600 l/m² locally, while the northeast of the country remained comparatively dry, with regional totals below 500 litres/m².</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Sunshine in 2024 was slightly above climatological expectations. At just under 1,700 hours, sunshine duration in 2024 was above the target of 1544 hours (period 1961 to 1990). This also applies in comparison to the more recent reference period 1991 to 2020 (1665 hours). With up to 2,000 hours of sunshine, the highest values in Germany were measured from the Leipzig lowland bay to Upper Lusatia and the Baltic Sea coast in particular. In parts of western Germany, on the other hand, the sun often only shone for around 1500 hours.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The weather in the federal states (Bundesländer)</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_e5c86f6fa266450a8ecb27830da51235~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="German weather abnormalities 1881 to 2024"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Baden-Württemberg</strong></p>
<p>In Baden-Württemberg, 2024 was the warmest year since measurements began in 1881. With an average temperature of 10.8 degrees, the record value of 10.7 degrees from 2023 was exceeded last year.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In 2024, Baden-Württemberg experienced the mildest winter since measurements began. A very wintry phase in the second and third week of January initially brought icy temperatures. The nationwide annual low of minus 19.5 degrees was measured in Leutkirch-Herlazhofen (Ravensburg district) on 20 January.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>February then brought a temperature deviation of plus 6 degrees and heralded the start of a record-breaking warm spring. According to the DWD, the summer was also too hot, sometimes characterised by heavy thunderstorms. The highest temperature in Germany for 2024 was measured at 36.5 degrees on 13 August in Bad Neuenahr-Ahrweiler in Rhineland-Palatinate.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Bayern (Bavaria)</strong></p>
<p>Temperatures in Bavaria reached a new average record in 2024. The German Weather Service reported an average temperature of 10.3 degrees. This is the second time in a row that the ten-degree mark has been exceeded. At the same time, precipitation rose by twelve per cent above the long-term average. This is accelerated climate change.’ May and September, in particular, were far too wet in Bavaria. This resulted, among other things, in flooding on the Danube in June.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Berlin &amp; Brandenburg</strong></p>
<p>Heat record in Berlin and Brandenburg: the average temperature in 2024 was higher than since measurements began. The year 2024 was the warmest in Berlin and Brandenburg since comprehensive measurements began in 1881, but it was also too wet, according to an assessment by the German Weather Service (DWD).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the report, the average temperature in the German capital was 11.9 degrees Celsius, 2.8 degrees above the value for the reference period from 1961 to 1990. In Brandenburg, the average temperature was 11.4 degrees. It was, therefore, 2.7 degrees higher than the long-term average.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the DWD, the previous record year in the region was 2019, when the DWD recorded an average temperature of 11.1 degrees for Berlin and Brandenburg combined. Separate figures for 2019 for the two federal states are not available.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In both states, meteorologists recorded a rather mild winter and a rather warm spring in 2024. In September, there was a heatwave with peak values of 34.4 degrees in Berlin.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In Berlin, 582 litres of rain per square metre fell in 2024, slightly more than the average for the internationally valid reference period from 1961 to 1990 (573 litres). In Brandenburg, the annual precipitation in 2024 totalled around 600 litres per square metre. This is also more than the reference value (557 litres).</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Hamburg &amp; Schleswig Holstein</strong></p>
<p>Hamburg experienced a record average temperature in 2024, making it one of the warmest regions in Germany. The average of 11.4 degrees in the Hanseatic city was only surpassed by Berlin and Bremen, the German Weather Service wrote in its annual weather report. Hamburg thus experienced the warmest year since measurements began in 1881. In the internationally recognised reference period from 1961 to 1990, the average temperature in the Hanseatic city was 8.8 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The warmth was accompanied by large amounts of rain, which also led to localised flooding in individual events. Except for March and December, which were drier, the remaining months were, in some cases, unusually rainy. Around 993 litres per square metre fell in 2024. According to the statistics, 750 litres per square metre would have been expected.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Things didn&apos;t look much different in Schleswig-Holstein either: Germany&apos;s northernmost federal state experienced the warmest year since 1881. This was not reflected in long periods of summer heat but in the average temperature of 10.8 degrees. This means that the north was only 0.1 degrees below the national average of 10.9 degrees, according to the DWD. In Schleswig-Holstein, the average temperature in the internationally recognised reference period from 1961 to 1990 was 8.3 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Hessen (Hesse)</strong></p>
<p>In Hesse, 2024 began with the second mildest winter ever recorded. February set a new temperature record. According to the DWD, a new record was also set for the entire spring. In summer, August brought ‘torrential’ rainfall. Trendelburg in northern Hesse reported the highest daily total of the year in Germany, with 169.8 litres per square metre on 1 August. Overall, the DWD measured an average of 868 litres per square metre for the year 2024 in Hesse, which is significantly more than the target from the reference period of 793 litres per square metre.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Niedersachsen (Lower Saxony)</strong></p>
<p>The year 2024 began in Lower Saxony with flooded cellars, roads and fields. However, the flood was just one of several striking weather events. According to official figures, the Christmas flood of 2023/2024 was one of the worst natural disasters the state has ever experienced. Historic levels of rainfall, nationwide flooding and immense damage called on all available resources in the country and many more beyond. The financial damage was well more than 100 million euros.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Nordrhein-Wesrfalen (North-Rhine Westphalia)</strong></p>
<p>The weather in NRW in 2024 was exceptionally warm and, at the same time, characterised by high rainfalls. With an average temperature of 11.2 degrees, NRW equalled the record values of 2022 and 2023, according to the DWD.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The measured average temperature of 11.2 degrees is well above the reference value of 9 degrees from the period 1961 to 1990. The mild winter of 2023/2024 already indicated the trend towards warmth. February was particularly striking, with temperatures comparable to a typical April month. March and spring also continued this trend with record-breaking high temperatures. A changeable summer was followed by an autumn that was also too warm.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Rheinland-Pflalz (Rhineland-Palatinate)</strong></p>
<p>An average of 10.9 degrees was measured in Rhineland-Palatinate in 2024. This corresponds to the average temperature for the whole of Germany. This is 2.7 degrees above the value of the internationally recognised reference period from 1961 to 1990. Compared to the current and warmer reference period from 1991 to 2020, the increase was 1.6 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the DWD, it was remarkably warm in spring and August. Spring had already begun in February. On 13 August, the thermometer in Bad Neuenahr rose to 36.5 degrees, setting the nationwide heat record for the year.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Saarland</strong></p>
<p>The year 2024 was far too warm and far too wet in Saarland. The average temperature was 11.2 degrees, well above the long-term average of 8.9 degrees. The value of 11.2 degrees for the whole year is not a record for Saarland - the year 2022 was the warmest here to date at 11.6 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Sachsen (Saxony)</strong></p>
<p>Saxony had already experienced record temperatures in 2023 - but 2024 set new standards with even higher values and extreme weather events. Weather experts reported record warmth for Saxony in 2024. The average temperature was 10.7 degrees Celsius. The previous average for the international reference period from 1961 to 1990 was 8.1 degrees Celsius. Last winter was the second mildest since records began, followed by a record-warm spring. And on 4 September, Leipzig reported a new heat record for the month at 34.9 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>With a daily rainfall of more than 100 litres per square metre, an extremely heavy rainfall event between Dresden and the Eastern Ore Mountains caused flooding on 18 August. A total of 752 litres of precipitation per square metre fell in Saxony, which is above the long-term average of 699 litres.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Autumn continued the unusually warm temperatures.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Thüringen (Thuringia)</strong></p>
<p>Thuringia had already set a temperature record in 2023. Now, it&apos;s gone up again. Exceptionally warm days in February and spring brought Thuringia another temperature record in 2024. Compared to the previous year, the average value climbed by 0.3 degrees to 10.4 degrees.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>This was one of the lowest values in a comparison of the federal states. Across Germany, the average values also climbed by 0.3 degrees to a record 10.9 degrees. ‘This is accelerated climate change,’ explained DWD spokesperson Uwe Kirsche in Offenbach. In Thuringia, the peak value was mainly the result of record temperatures in February and spring, he added. August was the second warmest since records began. And autumn was also unusually warm. On 4 September, 34.6 degrees were measured in Tegkwitz in Altenburger Land.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Source:</strong> Deutscher Wetterdienst (German Weather Service)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>On other pages:</strong> <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/city-trees" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Trees in German cities</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/green-cities" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Germany&apos;s greenest cities</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">In your opinion</a> |</p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Taleb al-Abdulmohsen ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Anti-Islamist allegedly responsible for the Christmas horror of Magdeburg]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/taleb-al-abdulmohsen</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6766e25dd361a658c7048da7</guid><category><![CDATA[Terrorism]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 16:07:42 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Anti-Islamist allegedly responsible for the Christmas horror of Magdeburg</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_fb2547d374c441b28ea2953f1f1acb7a~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Taleb al-Abdulmohsen, the alleged attacker of Magdeburg's Christmas market"></figure>
<p>Screenshot of Taleb al-Abdulmohsen’s X (Twitter) account. The suspect of the attack on Magdeburg’s Christmas market claims that Germany intends to Islamise Europe</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>December 2024:</strong> The 50-year Saudi doctor, who is suspected of driving at great speed into a crowded Christmas market in Magdeburg (Eastern Germany) on 20 December 2024, has emerged as an outspoken anti-Islamist. Taleb al-Abdulmohsen has posted countless rumbling comments on social media in which he claimed <span style="color: rgb(51, 51, 51);">that German politicians were deliberately trying to ‘Islamise’ the country. He also expressed his admiration for Germany’s far-right </span><em><span style="color: rgb(51, 51, 51);">AfD (Alternative for Germany)</span></em><span style="color: rgb(51, 51, 51);"> party and his hatred for Angela Merkel, Germany’s former Chancellor.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Earlier this month (December 2024), he speculated on X/Twitter about Merkel&apos;s alleged criminal secret project to Islamise Europe. “As there is no death penalty in Germany, Merkel must spend the rest of her life in prison”, Taleb al-Abdulmohsen wrote in English. “But if the death penalty is reintroduced, she deserves to be killed.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The attack on Magdeburg’s Christmas market caused the immediate death of five people. Among the 200 people injured, 40 are thought to be in critical condition. The number of fatalities is, therefore, expected to rise.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The suspect had not previously come to the attention of the authorities as an extremist. On the contrary, in an interview with the <em>Frankfurter Rundschau (FR)</em> newspaper in 2019, Taleb al-Abdulmohsen presented himself as an activist who wanted to help other people. However, there is a lot of evidence online that proves his radicalisation.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the German news magazine <em>Der Spiegel</em>, the suspect was born in the Saudi Arabian city of Hufuf. He came to Germany in March 2006 as a visiting doctor training to become a psychotherapist. In July 2016, he is said to have been recognised as a refugee and received a permanent residence permit. The reason for this was his renunciation of Islam and the death threats to which he was subsequently subjected.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In the interview with the <em>Frankfurter Rundschau</em>, Taleb al-Abdulmohsen explained that he informs women from Saudi Arabia about the German asylum system to show them a safe way out of their home country. He created a website to help women do this. The British broadcaster BBC also published a video about his efforts as an activist in 2019.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The German daily newspaper <em>Die Welt</em> reported that Taleb al-Abdulmohsen described himself as an ex-Muslim. He spread the claim that Germany wanted to ‘Islamise’ Europe. He also wrote: “Germany hunts Saudi asylum seekers inside and outside Germany to destroy their lives.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The suspect also appears to sympathise with the AfD, as reported by Der Spiegel. In other posts on X, he is said to have fantasised about joint projects with the AfD. He is said to have imagined an academy for ex-Muslims. He wrote: “Who else is fighting Islam in Germany?” According to a report by <em>AFP</em>, he allegedly labelled the left as crazy and wrote the following about the AfD: “We need the AfD to protect the police from themselves.”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><em><strong>Sources: </strong></em><em>X (Twitter) account of Taleb al-Abdulmohsen; D</em>er Spiegel; Die Welt; Frankfurter Rundschau; The Telegraph; AFP and other news outlets</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Also worth reading:</strong> <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/brief-german-news" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">News from Germany</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/in-depth-news" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">News analysis from Germany</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-sports-news" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Football news</a> |</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Margot Friedlander Holocaust survivor]]></title><description><![CDATA[Holocaust survivor Margot Friedländer: There is no Christian, Muslim or Jewish blood. There is only human blood]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/margot-friedlander-holocaust-survivor</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6731ea3fc7e8a67d867734f3</guid><category><![CDATA[Women]]></category><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 12:02:14 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">Holocaust survivor Margot Friedländer</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">There is no Christian, Muslim or Jewish blood. There is only human blood</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_d75c04c3ced544df8291ee8e82d2a691~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Margot Friedländer - Holocaust survivor"></figure>
<p>Margot Friedländer in 2024 in her Berlin apartment and the women&apos;s barracks in the Nazi ghetto Theresienstadt in 1943</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>November 2024: </strong>There are still around 240,000 Holocaust survivors in the world. One of them is Margot Friedländer, who celebrated her 103rd birthday this month. On this occasion, she was awarded the <em>Golden Bambi</em>, the German Oscar. She received the award for the courage that has characterised her entire life. Even today, at her age, she speaks out against inhumanity. She visits schools and universities and talks to people from all walks of life, to people from all over the world. She repeatedly emphasises that human rights are universal. They apply to everyone. Especially now, when in Germany and many other countries, attempts are being made to separate people according to origin, religion and gender, we must honour human commonalities. Margot Friedländer said, ‘There is no Christian, Muslim or Jewish blood. There is only human blood.’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Margot Friedländer was born Margot Bendheim in Berlin in 1921. After finishing school, she worked as an apprentice in a tailor&apos;s shop. Her family&apos;s efforts to emigrate to the USA were unsuccessful. From 1940, Margot had to perform forced labour. After her parents separated, she lived with her mother and younger brother Ralph. They planned to flee in 1943, but Ralph was arrested by the Gestapo. The mother then handed herself into the Gestapo and was deported to Auschwitz with her son and murdered. She left her daughter a message: ‘Try to make a life for yourself’. The 21-year-old went into hiding, was detained by <em>Greifers / Snatchers (Jews that were paid by the Nazis to catch fellow Jews)</em> in 1944 and deported to Theresienstadt concentration camp. She was the only family member to survive the camp. Margot went to the USA in 1946 with her husband, Adolph Friedländer, whom she knew from Berlin and whom she met again in Theresienstadt. She has lived in Berlin again since 2010. <strong>(1)</strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Every 9 November, the world remembers the pogrom night of 1938 <em>(Kristallnacht)</em>, and Margot Friedländer still recalls the day after. In an interview, she described what she experienced the morning following the night of destruction. <strong>(2)</strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p>“I came out of the flat and immediately realised that there were fewer people on the street than normal. I was on my way to work. There was a funny smell in the air. I soon saw the first shops with uniformed people standing outside and broken shop windows. And I also saw people taking things from the shops and what was already on the street. As much as they could carry.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“I was only gone for ten or 15 minutes and then returned home. When I left, it was still very quiet. And when I came back, everyone knew that the synagogues were on fire, even though we didn&apos;t have a radio or a telephone. My mum and my brother were waiting for me and were very devastated. They already knew what was going on. My parents were divorced, and we were naturally worried about where my father was. It took days for him to get in touch. He had gone into hiding. It was very tragic.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Margot Friedländer also remembers Hitler&apos;s rise to power. “I was less than twelve years old at the time and perhaps still had a small hope that it would all blow over. In 1935, my aunt and uncle emigrated to Brazil. My father said: “Hitler won&apos;t last. I&apos;m not giving up my business, and I&apos;m staying.” “You can always come back,” was all my uncle said. In 1939, my father was given a passport because he had to introduce the new ‘Aryan’ owner of his shop to the foreign suppliers. My parents were already divorced by then. My father travelled abroad in 1939, and we never saw him again.’ <strong>(3)</strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p>In January 1943, the <em>Gestapo (the Nazi secret police)</em> arrested Margot&apos;s brother, Ralph. Her mother, who was not at home at the time, then turned herself in. “She didn&apos;t want to leave Ralph alone.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Being left without family, Margot Friedländer then lived in hiding for a year. She underwent a nose operation to avoid looking too Jewish and dyed her hair red. She wore a chain with a cross around her neck. She was able to escape the Gestapo three times, and time and time again, strangers hid her. “These people did something that could have cost them their lives, but they didn&apos;t hesitate. I am infinitely grateful for that.” What Margot did not know, however, was that there were Jews who were paid by the Nazis to betray other Jews to save their own lives. “I was caught by Jewish <em>snatchers</em>.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Margot Friedländer now views events in present-day Germany and also in America, the country that offered her a home in 1946, with great concern. When politicians from the German far-wing scene refer to the Nazi era as a blip in German history, she shudders: “The frightening thing is that people like them and anti-Semitism have always co-existed. Unfortunately, I can&apos;t predict anything for the future. I can only tell what happened and how I feel. I am very worried that something could happen again, and I say I warn you against it.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Margot Friedländer is also troubled by the division in American society. “I have many friends and relatives there. They are afraid.” <strong>(4)</strong> American President Joe Biden wrote to her, expressing his admiration for her strength and commitment to sharing her memories with young people across the world.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>Sources:</em></p>
<p><em>1) Jüdisches Museum Berlin (Jewish Museum in Berlin).</em></p>
<p><em>2) Westdeutscher Rundfunk (Public service broadcaster)</em></p>
<p><em>3) Neue Zürcher Zeitung (Swiss daily newspaper)</em></p>
<p><em>4) Margot Friedländer spoke before the election of Donald Trump on 5 November 2024</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>On other pages: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German mayors against the far-right</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/business-against-far-right" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German business against far-right populism</a> | <a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to reject the far-right</a> |</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[German Book Prize 2024]]></title><description><![CDATA[German Book Prize 2024: A novel about loneliness, lies and love (Hey guten Morgen, wie geht es Dir?)]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-book-prize-2024</link><guid isPermaLink="false">67264148a64c34db14c9d659</guid><category><![CDATA[The Arts]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 15:35:01 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">GERMAN BOOK PRIZE 2024</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">‘Hey guten Morgen, wie geht es Dir?’</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">‘Hey, good morning, how are you?’</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_9f99a0dfb83f4944b87f864a36cb1bd5~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Martina Hefter, winner of the 2024 German Book Prize"></figure>
<p>Martina Hefter&apos;s novel &apos;Hey guten Morgen, wie geht es Dir?&apos; (Hey, good good morning, how are you?) won the 2024 German Book Prize</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>A novel about loneliness, lies and love</strong></p>
<p><strong>November 2024:</strong> Juno, the heroine of the novel that won the German Book Prize 2024, (Deutscher Buchpreis 2024) helps her seriously ill husband, Jupiter, cope with his everyday life during the day. She is also an artist, dances and plays theatre. And at night, when she can&apos;t sleep again, she chats with love scammers on the internet. Author Martina Hefter has written a touching novel about needs and desires in life. And about how far one is prepared to go for love.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In Martina Hefter&apos;s novel <em>‘Hey guten Morgen, wie geht es Dir?’ (‘Hey, good morning, how are you?’)</em>, the reader meets Juno, who chats with men online. These men confess their love to women and try to trick them out of their money. But instead of falling for it, these very men become a form of freedom for Juno. In the conversations, she can be who she wants and say what she wants - and supposedly without consequences. This is in stark contrast to her other life, in which she is always on the move, always worried about her husband Jupiter, and always busy and involved. So Juno occasionally escapes from her everyday life onto the internet and plays games with men who lie to her. She also becomes a liar<strong>.</strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p>One day, Juno meets Benu, a Nigerian man, who sees through her claims just as she sees through his. And despite the distance between them, a connection develops. ‘Hey, good morning, how are you’ is a profound novel but as light-footed as a comedy. The novel is also about ageing, colonialism, longing, friendship and love. The author deals with these major themes laconically and delicately.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Deutschlandfunk writes about </strong><em><strong>‘Hey Good morning, how are you?&apos;</strong></em><strong>  by Martina Hefter:</strong></p>
<p>“The German police are issuing an urgent warning about love scammers. Their website states: ‘’Love scamming&apos; or “romance scamming” is the modern form of marriage fraud. Scammers create fake profiles on social media platforms or dating portals and pretend to be in love. In the end, however, they only have one goal: they want to get their victims&apos; money!’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Author and dance performer Martina Hefter, who hails from the Allgäu region, must have thought she could capitalise on this in a literary way. In her new novel ‘Hey good morning, how are you?’, she sends her heroine into the world of fake flirts.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Juno Isabella Flock is a woman in her mid-fifties who lives in Leipzig and works as an independent dancer. A dancer without spatial orientation, however, who lives with a man suffering from a severe form of multiple sclerosis. A woman who repeatedly escapes into the dance hall to experience weightlessness. A man for whom a journey by train becomes a high-performance exercise that he could hardly manage without his wife. Juno and Jupiter are the names of the two in the novel.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>This is not a harmless invention: in the author&apos;s life, there is her husband, the author Jan Kuhlbrodt, who suffers from the same illness. While Jupiter lies in his nursing bed, Juno begins a double life with her love scammer in the next room - fully aware of the artificiality of the situation. It&apos;s not just the marriage scammer with the chic profile picture of a white senior employee who constructs an illusory world. Juno also uses the exchange to be someone else.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>It is not the quality of the dialogue with which the author scores points. Rather, it is the complete lack of originality that brings our neediness to light in a sobering way. What is it that makes women fall in droves into the nets of such swindlers, most of whom are not middle-class white men from Europe but poor black men from Africa?</p>
<p>Just like Benu from a medium-sized Nigerian town in the south of the country, where the electricity is switched off from 11 p.m., which is why the video calls that the two soon switch to are played by candlelight.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Benu, who now recognises himself for who he is, becomes a witness to a false identity in this pose. For him, Juno is a woman with many lovers, without a husband, a successful dancer in her prime, and, in short, a woman to fall in love with!</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Martina Hefter has choreographed her text. She plays around with different versions of a personality, different states, and different moral standpoints in a language that doesn&apos;t shy away from moments of bleakness any more than the love scammers do: stale compliments, pseudo-deep meaning about the stars, dullness about dance training. Strangely enough, however, the tedium in this novel remains the programme.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Neither Benu&apos;s story nor at least his perspective is told (he only changes numbers one day), nor that of a woman who cares for her sick husband and lives a different concept of love here. Nor has this become a text about the language of the body. Juno can praise her long dancing legs as often as she likes. All this would only be half as wild if Hefter didn&apos;t also want to criticise capitalism and power.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>In the Westdeutscher Rundfunk, Ulrich Noller writes about </strong><em><strong>‘Hey, Good morning, how are you?’</strong></em><strong>  by Martina Hefter.</strong></p>
<p>“With playful ease into the shallows of life, poetic and precise, Martina Hefter&apos;s autofictional novel tells a very personal story of the present.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Martina Hefter tells a love triangle story, but with a silent partner: Juno, around 50, is a dancer and performance artist who lives with her partner in Leipzig under precarious circumstances as a cultural worker. Her husband is the person in the next room, whom she looks after and cares for because he is chronically ill. Jupiter, as she calls him, remains pale; he plays a role more in outline.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Juno is attentive and loving; however, she is also fully committed, and her caring responsibilities regulate and determine her life. She finds freedom online By communicating with love scammers, guys who use fake profiles to build relationships with lonely women to siphon off their wealth. At least virtually, Juno has such wealth, and she takes the freedom to play her games, just as the scammers play with her.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>But then she ‘meets’ Benu, a 32-year-old from Nigeria. The two find something about each other; a virtual relationship develops out of the games, which increasingly develops elements of something ‘real’. Where can this lead?</p>
<p>‘Hey, good morning, how are you?’ is many things in one: an artist&apos;s novel, a memoir, a diagnosis of the times, a relationship story. Martina Hefter conjures up all these dimensions with a light hand, playfully, focussed, precise and always highly poetic as she juggles the balls over the abyss of life&apos;s shallows - her own life. Well, at least to a certain extent, it is a semi-fictional text that dances on the edge.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>The German Book Prize</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: black;">The German Book Prize (Deutscher Buchpreis) is presented to the best German-language novel just before the start of the annual Frankfurt Book Fair. The Prize is intended to draw attention beyond national borders to authors writing in German. Publishing companies can apply for the award by direct nomination of their titles. Unusually, titles still in production when applications are first invited can also be included in the selection process. Furthermore, the German Book Prize represents the guarantee of independent and competent prize judgment: the seven jurors will personally assess all the books that are submitted and that meet the criteria for consideration.</span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>On other pages: <span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">| </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/hertha-gordon-walcher" rel="noreferrer">Hertha Gordon-Walcher</a></span><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/martin-walser" rel="noreferrer">Martin Walser</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> </span><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">|</span><span style="color: #D21111;"> </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/books" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German Book Prize 2023</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> </span><span style="color: #012055;">|</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #012055;">In your opinion: </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Praise. Criticise. Write</a></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[German Youth Word 2024]]></title><description><![CDATA[German youths have chosen their favourite words]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-youth-word-2024</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6713ce0106882a2a132922c5</guid><category><![CDATA[The Arts]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 15:39:28 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">GERMAN YOUTH  WORD 2024</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">German youths have chosen their favourite words</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_88a70d97153844e5991014893ee841cf~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="German Youth word 2024"></figure>
<p>German youths between 11 and 20 have chosen &apos;Talahon&apos; as their second-favourite word of 2024. (Image of Talahan youths: AI created on TikTok)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>October 2024:</strong> Young Germans have chosen their favourite words for 2024. Following an online vote in which 11 to 20-year-olds participated, the renowned language publisher Langenscheidt published a longlist of ten words. The list included words or terms such as Digga, Hölle nein, Schere, Yolo, Talahon, Aura and Akh.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In the end, Aura, Talahon and Schere were the most popular words.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Aura</strong></p>
<p>In social media, the term is particularly widespread in the context of sports. Athletes or coaches are said to have an aura. According to the competition organisers Langenscheidt, the word first found its new use in 2020 in an article in the New York Times about the Dutch footballer Virgil van Dijk. Since then, ‘aura’ has become a common word in sports.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Talahon</strong></p>
<p>Talahon is derived from Arabic and originally means ‘come here’. According to Langenscheidt, the term Talahon(s) refers to young men who wear fake luxury clothes and walk through the city centre with Gucci bags, tracksuit bottoms and gold chains to make themselves important.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The term Talahon is considered controversial, and in some cases, Talahon is also seen as discriminatory. This is because it often refers to young men with a migration background. This year, the term caused controversy and sometimes racist discussions about migration and youth culture. The word is categorised somewhere between racism, resentment and self-irony. Discriminatory terms are usually an exclusion criterion for the jury - but in the case of Talahon, the Langenscheidt panel did not consider this to be the case. “The group addressed young men with a stereotypical appearance, also jokingly refer to themselves in this way without any discriminatory meaning,” the publisher explained.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The AI song <em>‘Ich glaub ich bin verknallt in einen Talahon’</em> (I think, I’m in love with a Talahon) is currently one of the most played songs on German TikTok.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Schere (scissors)</strong></p>
<p>‘Schere’ or ‘die Schere heben’ (lifting the scissors) comes from the gaming world and expresses an admission of guilt or a confession. ‘I played Fortnite yesterday but had to lift the scissors (mußte die Schere heben).’</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>The longlist 2024</strong></p>
<p>Yurr</p>
<p>Used as an agreement and greeting. It can therefore mean ‘yes’ or ‘what&apos;s up’. ‘Yurr! What went on at the weekend?’ (Yurr! Was ging am Wochenende?)</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Nein Pascal, ich denke nicht</p>
<p>Expression of rejection, especially when a person has unrealistic expectations. ‘If he expects you to get in touch first and then plan all the dates. – No, Pascal, I don&apos;t think so.’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Scissors</p>
<p>A term used in online games to express an admission of guilt or confession.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Hölle, nein</p>
<p>Expresses strong disapproval, like the English ‘Hell no’. “Are you coming on Saturday? Hell no!’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Pyrotechnics</p>
<p>Expresses support for pyrotechnics at sporting events, such as football stadiums. ‘Pyrotechnics are not a crime. We will fight for it!’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Talahon</p>
<p>Originates from Arabic and means ‘come here’. Describes people with stereotypical behaviour and characteristics.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Yolo</p>
<p>Stands for You Only Live Once. Used to justify impulsive or risky decisions.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Akh</p>
<p>The greeting of friends of Arabic origin.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Digga (Bro) Form of address for friends and acquaintances.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Aura</p>
<p>Athletes or coaches are said to have an aura.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>Methodology</em></p>
<p><em>According to the information provided, the voting included terms that are regularly used by teenagers and young adults aged 11 to 20. The frequency and use of the terms were checked on platforms such as Instagram, TikTok and Reddit. ‘If a term was categorised as widespread and frequently used, and was not specifically initiated by a campaign and therefore not fake, it remained in the running.’ According to the press release, terms with clearly offensive, discriminatory or sexist connotations were excluded. The ‘Youth Word of the Year’ has existed since 2008.</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Juergen Klopp joins Red Bull]]></title><description><![CDATA[German football legend Jürgen Klopp joins Red Bull to the disappointment of his fans]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/juergen-klopp-joins-red-bull</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6708127295cdbbf415264617</guid><category><![CDATA[Sport]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 18:00:44 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>German football legend Jürgen Klopp joins Red Bull to the disappointment of his fans</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_b2edb5fd52a3411aaa06f47fda1e0eb5~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Jürgen Klopp joins Red Bull"></figure>
<p>Jürgen Klopp was football coach at FSV Mainz 05, Borussia Dortmund, before joining Liverpool FC in 2015, where he remained until the end of the 2023/24 season</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>October 2024:</strong> Juergen Klopp, who is already a legend at Liverpool, was awarded the German Order of Merit on 1 October 2024. At the award ceremony, German President Walter Steinmeier said: “Success and fame have never deterred Juergen Klopp from turning his attention to each athlete and seeing the human being in them. He has thus become a great role model for many - and an outstanding football ambassador far beyond the world of sport.” Now, the Austrian soft drinks manufacturer Red Bull has recruited him as an ambassador for its brand. “Klopp will work for Red Bull as ‘Global Head of Soccer,” said a company spokesman. It is not known whether Germany’s President was told of Klopp’s link to Red Bull.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Jürgen Klopp, who had every coaching job in the world open to him if he wanted it, has now committed himself to the world of commerce, even if he perhaps doesn&apos;t see it that way. “After almost 25 years on the touchline, I couldn&apos;t be more excited to be involved in a project like this,” Klopp said in Red Bull&apos;s corporate statement. “My role may have changed, but my passion for football and the people who make the game what it is has not.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“By joining Red Bull at a global level, I want to develop, improve and support the incredible football talent we have at our disposal. There are many ways we can do this, utilising the cutting-edge knowledge and experience that Red Bull has and learning from other sports and industries. Together, the Red Bull team and I can discover what is possible,” the former Liverpool and Dortmund manager explained.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Above all, Klopp wants to pull the strings behind the scenes. “I see my role primarily as a mentor for the coaches and management of the Red Bull clubs, but ultimately, I am part of an organisation that is unique, innovative and future-oriented. As I said, this couldn&apos;t excite me more.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>At Red Bull, Klopp is likely primarily responsible for the international network and the strategic orientation of all football clubs under the Red Bull umbrella. In addition to the clubs RB Leipzig and RB Salzburg, Red Bull also operates New York Red Bulls, Brazilian club Red Bull Bragantino and Omiya Ardija (Japan). Red Bull’s latest football acquisition is a 15% stake in the French second-division club Paris FC, which is majority-owned by the Arnault family (LVMH).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Juergen Klopp&apos;s appointment as Head of Global Soccer for Red Bull has prompted a strong reaction from football fans and the international sports press.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>ZDF (German national broadcaster)</strong></p>
<p>“There&apos;s no question that when Jürgen Klopp becomes ‘Head of Global Soccer’ at Red Bull on 1 January, it will be a punch in the gut for football romantics. Especially as Jürgen Klopp has always emphasised in interviews that he is a football romantic.” But the broadcaster adds: “But how much purity, how much romance is there left in this football, in which simple sports clubs have developed into globally operating football companies, with many listed on the stock exchange?”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Focus (German news magazine)</strong></p>
<p>For the traditionalists among football fans, Juergen Klopp&apos;s move is a blatant betrayal of everything he has stood for throughout his career. FSV Mainz 05, Borussia Dortmund and Liverpool FC were his stations. Big fan scenes, rough working-class towns, pure passion, accompanied by the anthem of all anthems, ‘You&apos;ll Never Walk Alone’. Klopp was the broadly grinning face of football romance. The magazine adds: ‘In financial matters, Klopp is an opportunist. Thanks to his popularity, he landed himself heaps of advertising deals over the years. The job at Red Bull should also be seen in this light.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Frankfurter Rundschau (German daily newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“For many, the Red Bull brand, which stands for the commercialisation of professional football like no other, is not suited to Klopp, who worked exclusively for traditional clubs during his coaching career. Klopp has ‘sold his legendary status to Red Bull’, commented a stunned fan under an Instagram.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>The Salzburger Nachrichten (Austrian daily newspaper)</strong></p>
<p> “Klopp coup: No Red Bull transfer has ever been bigger. Watching Jürgen Klopp at work has inevitably made me want to play football. He can give Red Bull football a soul.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>The Guardian (British daily newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“Jürgen Klopp shakes English football’s god delusion with embrace of Red Bull. This feels like the kind of thing you do when you’re still not sure what you want to do. Grandiose job title aside, the brief itself feels reassuringly vague. “I want to see, feel and figure out what is useful for football,” Klopp said. “Developing football a little bit as well.” As a sacred mission statement, ‘turning doubters into believers’ this is not.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Daily Mirror (British daily newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“Jürgen Klopp takes on his first job since leaving Liverpool FC. It is unlikely that Klopp will immediately return to the front line of football in his new role. Instead, he will lend his expertise to the Red Bull football group.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>The Athletic (British sports magazine)</strong></p>
<p>“When an emotional Klopp bid farewell to Anfield in May, he insisted he wanted to take a full year off to recharge his batteries. (...) Given his passion for football and the numerous job offers he has received, it is hardly surprising that the 57-year-old has decided to end his sabbatical early.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Gazzetta dello Sport (Italian sports newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“Role change. Klopp is back.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Marca (Spanish sports newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“The global energy drinks group, which has made a name for itself as a patron of numerous sports, has been able to win over the sought-after German football coach Jürgen Klopp to lead the strategic vision for Red Bull football clubs around the world.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Blick (Swiss daily newspaper)</strong></p>
<p>“Footballing hammer. Red Bull gets Jürgen Klopp. Germany&apos;s iconic coach Jürgen Klopp has a new job: he is joining Red Bull&apos;s football organisation.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>Jürgen Klopp was coach at FSV Mainz 05, Borussia Dortmund, before joining Liverpool FC in 2015, where he remained until the end of the 2023/24 season. He was named World Coach of the Year in 2019 and 2020. Commenting on his last position as a coach, the Office of the German President said: “From Liverpool, the most popular German in Great Britain has made a significant contribution to a positive image of our country.”</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="#asi2e286" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/christian-streich-freiburg" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>Tears flowed as Freiburg said goodbye to football coach Christian Streich</strong></a><strong> | </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-football-index" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>German Football Index</strong></a><strong> | </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-sports-news" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>German football news</strong></a><strong> |</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quo vadis Herbert Kickl]]></title><description><![CDATA[Austrian right-wing party, FPÖ, wins the 2024 election but lacks coalition partners]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/quo-vadis-herbert-kickl</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66faab20393733226fb89a99</guid><category><![CDATA[Europe]]></category><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 14:03:15 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Austria’s centrist parties have failed to agree on a coalition government. It may be the far-right&apos;s turn</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_507e59f16246440c9ad69f650f21ebe7~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Centrist parties asked to form Austrian government"></figure>
<p>Thousands of people demonstrated in Vienna against the far-right FPÖ party. But after failed coalition talks between centrist parties, there is now a real possibility that the FPÖ will lead a new government. New elections are also a possibility.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>In Austria, after the election is before the election</strong></p>
<p><strong>January 2025:</strong> Austrian coalition talks between the Conservatives (ÖVP), Social Democrats (SPÖ) and Liberals (NEOs) have failed. In the election on 29 September 2024, the right-wing populists (FPÖ) emerged victorious, albeit without achieving an absolute majority. Federal President Alexander van der Bellen instructed the ÖVP and SPÖ to begin negotiations with the NEOs on a coalition government to prevent a right-wing government. These have now failed.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>At the moment, it is unclear how to proceed. The current Federal Chancellor, Karl Nehammer of the ÖVP, wants to resign. The Federal President intends to comment on the situation as early as today (5 January 2025).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>There is now a possibility that the FPÖ will be asked to try and form a governing coalition. If this is not possible, new elections cannot be ruled out. The far-right party is leading in the polls.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Austria’s conservatives and Social Democrats in coalition talks. A third partner may be required</strong></p>
<p><strong>October 2024: </strong>The two runners-up of Austria’s general election of 29 September 2024 have been tasked by the country’s federal president to form a government. President Alexander van der Bellen has asked the leader of the centre-right ÖVP (Austrian Peoples Party) to begin negotiations with the centre-left SPÖ (Social Democrats). At this stage, it is not quite clear whether the two parties have enough seats for a parliamentary majority. They may need to find a third partner, with the liberal NEOS or the Greens under consideration.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>President van der Bellen’s approach is unusual, as the ÖVP was only the second-strongest party in the parliamentary elections at the end of September. The right-wing populist FPÖ (Austrian Freedom Party) emerged as the winner, but all parties rejected it as a government partner. The President, who plays a central role in the formation of the government, did, therefore, not automatically ask the party with the most votes to form the government, as is usually the case.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The SPÖ, the NEOS, and the Greens all reject cooperation with the FPÖ in principle, while the ÖVP had previously ruled out a coalition led by FPÖ leader Herbert Kickl.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Before asking the <u>ÖVP to form a government, the Austrian President </u>called on the leaders of the three largest parties to sound out possible coalitions among themselves. After the talks, both the ÖVP and SPÖ declared that they would maintain their negative stance towards the FPÖ. Karl Nehammer (ÖVP) categorially rejected a coalition with the FPÖ. “I will not be a stirrup holder for the far-right Herbert Kickl.”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Austrian right-wing party celebrates election win, but forming a government will be difficult</strong></p>
<p><strong>October 2024:</strong> Right-wing parties are on the rise in Europe. Following the successes of Italy&apos;s <em>Brothers of Italy</em>, the <em>Rassemblement National</em> in France and the <em>AfD (Alternative for Germany)</em> in eastern Germany, the majority of Austrian voters cast their ballots for the right-wing populist FPÖ. This is the first time since the Second World War that a right-wing party has become the strongest force in an Alpine republic.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>During the election campaign, Herbert Kickl, the FPÖ&apos;s candidate for Chancellor, blamed immigrants for all the ills in the country. He claimed that without immigrants, there would be no drug dealing, no rape and no terrorism in the country. However, he did not mention that the worst case of incest in Europe in modern times occurred in Austria. It was an Austrian, Josef Fritzl, who held his daughter captive in the cellar of the family home for 24 years and raped her regularly. She gave birth to seven children.</p>
<p> </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Austria’s political parties after the 2024 general election</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>FPÖ (Freedom Party of Austria) right-wing, 29.2% (58 seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>ÖVP (Austrian People’s Party) conservative, 26.5% (52 seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>SPÖ (Social Democratic Party of Austria) centre-left, 21.0% (41 seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>NEOS (The New Austrian and Liberal Forum) liberal, 9.0% (17 seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Die Grünen (The Greens) Environmental, 8.0% (15 seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>KPÖ (Communist Party of Austria) left-wing, 2.3% (No seats)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><strong>92 seats required for a parliamentary majority</strong></em></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p>Although Herbert Kickl announced his claim to the chancellorship immediately after the election, it is unlikely that he will find coalition partners. The current Austrian Chancellor, Karl Nehammer, has categorically ruled out serving in a government led by Kickl. According to their statements, all other parties represented in the Austrian parliament are not available as coalition partners for the FPÖ.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>A cooperation of the ÖVP without the FPÖ chairman is considered conceivable, although it is unlikely that Kickl will withdraw after his election triumph. During the election campaign, the FPÖ team named Kickl <em>Volkskanzler</em> (people’s chancellor), a term first used by the Nazis to describe Adolf Hitler.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The current governing coalition between the ÖVP and the Greens no longer has a parliamentary majority after the election. A coalition between the ÖVP and the centre-left SPÖ would be possible, although, in terms of content, the ÖVP has more in common with the FPÖ than with the Social Democrats. An ÖVP / SPÖ coalition would only have a narrow majority of one vote. Although there has never been a three-party coalition in Austria, a government of the ÖVP, the SPÖ and the Liberals (NEOS) would be plausible.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The current ÖVP-Greens coalition will offer its resignation, Austria&apos;s Federal President Alexander van der Bellen will accept it - and at the same time ask the previous Federal Chancellor Karl Nehammer to continue business with his old government until a new chancellor majority has been found in the National Council (Nationalrat), the Austrian parliament. In other words, a new ‘viable’ coalition, according to the Federal President.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Federal President added that a new Chancellor must have his confidence. “He must respect the cornerstones of our liberal democracy: The rule of law, separation of powers, human and minority rights, independent media and EU membership.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Representatives of European far-right parties expressed their delight at the FPÖ&apos;s election victory. The leader of the right-wing <em>Rassemblement National</em> in France, Jordan Bardella, wrote: ‘It fills us with great pride to sit in the European Parliament alongside our allies from the FPÖ, who won by a large margin in the parliamentary elections in Austria this evening. A government formed by the FPÖ will prioritise “the sovereignty, prosperity and identity of their country”. His party colleague Marine Le Pen added: “After the elections in Italy, the Netherlands and France, this upsurge, which involves the defence of national interests, the preservation of identities and the revival of sovereignty, confirms the triumph of the peoples everywhere.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Geert Wilders from the radical right-wing <em>Party for Freedom (PVV)</em> in the Netherlands also reacted: “Congratulations FPÖ”, Wilders wrote on X. In another post, he expressed his delight at the rise of right-wing parties in Europe. “We are winning! Times are changing,’ wrote the Dutch politician. “Identity, sovereignty, freedom and no more illegal immigration/asylum - that&apos;s what millions of Europeans are longing for!”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>On other pages: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/european-elections-2024" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>European election 2024</strong></a><strong> | </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/afd-eastern-germany" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong>Alternative for Germany (AfD) in eastern Germany</strong></span></a><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong>Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to their fellow citizens to reject the New Right</strong></span></a><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong>German campaign against the far-right</strong></span></a><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" target="_blank"><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong>Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</strong></span></a><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong> </strong></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank"><span style="color: rgb(210, 17, 17);"><strong>Please comment</strong></span></a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Business against far-right]]></title><description><![CDATA[German industry: Far-right populism harms business and destroys jobs]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/business-against-far-right</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66af77c844b644132f43c258</guid><category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 13:08:53 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>German industry: Far-right populism harms business and destroys jobs</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_68382363556a48c28deae217371908ca~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_299,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="German business against the far-right"></figure>
<p>Edeka (Germany’s leading retailer): “We love diversity and stand up against the far-right.” The retail chain emptied an entire supermarket and only left products produced exclusively in Germany. The result: astonished customers walking through a supermarket with almost empty shelves.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>August 2024:</strong> New state parliaments will be elected in Saxony and Thuringia on 1 September 2024 and, according to forecasts, it is likely that the far-right <em>AfD (Alternative for Germany) </em>will become the strongest party in both parliaments. Even if the right-wingers do not become part of a governing coalition, their successes would further divide the populations and lead to a loss of image both nationally and internationally. Companies in both states are already aware that foreign business partners regard the developments with incomprehension. Foreign skilled workers have also expressed unease and fear.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The business community in Saxony fears that the latest AfD poll results will damage the state&apos;s image. &quot;We have to remember that we are dependent on the best minds worldwide - in science as well as in industry and the skilled trades,&quot; said Sylvia Pfefferkorn, deputy spokesperson for the association <em>‘Wirtschaft für ein weltoffenes Sachsen’</em>. She added that it was becoming increasingly difficult to attract people to Saxony as a place to live.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Some companies have taken a clear stance against right-wing extremism. For example earlier this year, the retail giant Edeka published a video on its Instagram channel with the message: &quot;We love diversity and stand up against the right.” The company emptied an entire supermarket for the video and only left products produced exclusively in Germany. The result: astonished customers walking through a supermarket with almost empty shelves.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In addition to Edeka, other well-known companies such as Siemens, Adidas, Telekom and Zalando have taken a clear stance against right-wing extremism and warned against it. Some smaller companies are also taking a stand against right-wing extremism and the AfD - and sometimes quite creatively. For example, the Cologne brewery Malzmühle - a 160-year-old family brewery that is now in its fifth generation - has posted an online advertisement with the slogan &quot;Only our bottles are brown&quot;.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Germany’s Labour Minister, Hubertus Heil, called on the business community to take a stand against the right. Heil told journalists that he was happy to hear from any business representative who took a clear stance against the AfD and Nazis. &quot;We are an open society, and our economic success is also based on this.&quot; Germany is not an island. &quot;Our economy is internationally networked. This is another reason why we cannot afford racism and nationalism,&quot; warned the Social Democrat (SPD) politician. &quot;Qualified skilled workers, who we urgently need to attract to Germany, will only come if they can be sure that they will not be marginalised or even threatened here.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The President of the Federation of German Industries (BDI), Siegfried Russwurm, also warned against the AfD. As an exporting country, Germany benefits more than almost any other from cosmopolitanism, international cooperation and trade as well as European unification.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Saxony’s association of medium-sized companies told reporters that this was the first time they had intervened in an election campaign. &quot;We can&apos;t believe that in Germany, with our history, an extreme right-wing party like the AfD can even find voters.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p>The report <em>&apos;Report Mainz&apos;</em> by Germany’s national news channel <em>Tagesschau</em> spoke to 30 medium-sized and large companies in Saxony and Thuringia. According to the programme, some 67 per cent of companies expect the rise of the AfD to hurt their own business and the regional economy. Some 20 per cent believe that an AfD-led state government would lead to job cuts. In such a scenario, 77 per cent of businesses fear a brain drain and 90 per cent a loss of image.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In a separate study, the Mannheim-based research institute ZEW (Leibniz Centre for European Economic Research) investigated how right-wing populism affects the mobility of German and foreign skilled workers. The authors found that cities and regions in which right-wing populist parties and movements enjoy broad support are at a disadvantage when it comes to attracting domestic and foreign skilled workers.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em><strong>Sources: </strong></em><em>ARD/Tagesschau/Report Mainz; Bundesministerium für Arbeit und soziales; Edeka, Wirtschaft für ein weltoffenes Sachsen; Bundesverband der deutschen Industie; Brauerei Malzmühle</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/margot-friedlander-holocaust-survivor" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Margot Friedländer - Holocaust survivor</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/rainbow-flag-pirna" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Protestant parish and LGBT stand together against far-right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/afd-eastern-germany" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Alternative for Germany (AfD) in eastern Germany</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to their fellow citizens to reject the New Right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German campaign against the far-right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" target="_blank">Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"> </span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><strong><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank">Please comment</a></span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></span></strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rainbow Flag Pirna]]></title><description><![CDATA[German Protestant parish and LGBT community stand together against the far-right.]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/rainbow-flag-pirna</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6698fe47b1eee2bdfe88854d</guid><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 11:52:46 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">German Protestant parish and LGBT community stand together against the far-right</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_7b58be57c74349dc87f0ae62e0ac5b49~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Pirna Protestant parish flies the rainbow flag"></figure>
<p>Protestant parish in Pirna (Saxony): “The Rainbow Flag expresses our human diversity. It invites us to hold together the different colours of our lives, finds no spectrum for a brown-racist, devaluing character and is also a Christian image of the fact that for God this world should be as colourful, diverse and even flawed as we humans are (Genesis 9:17).”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Protestant church flies the rainbow flag in defiance of the local right-wing mayor.</strong></p>
<p><strong>July 2024: </strong>In a small town in the eastern German state of Saxony, the Protestant church is supporting the local LGBT community in its dispute with the town&apos;s right-wing mayor. The dispute began when the recently elected mayor of Pirna forbade the rainbow flag to be flown at the town hall on 17 May, the International Day against Homophobia and Transphobia. The Protestant parish raised the flag at the town’s parish church in response.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In a social media comment, the mayor then compared the rainbow flag to the swastika flag of the Third Reich.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Mayor Tim Lochner, who the far-right AfD party supports, wrote in a social media post, which has now been deleted, that people should not forget that swastika flags hung on the town’s church years ago. The church council of Pirna called the mayor&apos;s comparison difficult to bear and wrong.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Pirna’s parish priest added that the Protestant Church has recognised and repented of the mistakes made by parts of its institution during the Nazi era. He continued: “We do not want to make the mistakes of the past again today and want to boldly declare that openness and tolerance are part of our basic understanding. The rainbow flag is a good sign of this. It expresses human diversity.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>A spokesman for the LGBT community thanked the Protestant parish for its support and called the mayor&apos;s behaviour propaganda of the cheapest kind.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Unintentionally, Mayor Lochner&apos;s homophobic behaviour has attracted national and international attention to Pirna’s LGBT community. Celebrities from all over Germany came to the town for this year&apos;s Christopher Street Parade on 13 July. The organisers estimated that the number of participants doubled to 6,000 compared to previous years.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>A representative for the Saxon state government said in a speech in Pirna that everyone was free to love and live as they wished. In her speech, the minister expressly thanked the pastor and parish for their actions.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Statement by the church council on the hanging of the rainbow flag at Pirna&apos;s St Mary&apos;s Church</strong></p>
<p>(Extracts translated from German)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.kirche-pirna.de/Willkommen/Regenbogenfahne-an-der-Marienkirche/4230/" target="_blank">Full German version</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p>At its meeting on 9 April 2024, the church council of the Protestant parish of Pirna decided to express its solidarity with people who continue to be oppressed. That is why the rainbow flag was hung on St Mary&apos;s Church on 17 May, the International Day against Homo-, Bi-, Inter- and Transphobia and the 13th Christopher Street Day.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Phobia means fear. Fear of what is different for many people, how they feel and how they organise their lives, is always wrong if it does not result in a threat to their own living space. That is why fear, especially fuelled fear of people whose gender identity is different to my own, is not helpful. Fear of people who speak a different language or even hatred of people who stand up for positions other than our own in the democratic political spectrum is just as unhelpful. Fear paralyses and leads to segregation and, in the worst case to exclusion and even violence. It is important to take a stand against all of this because our Christian faith teaches us: ‘God has not given us the spirit of fear but of power and love and prudence.’ (2 Timothy 1:7)</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The rainbow flag is a good symbol of this. It expresses our human diversity. It invites us to hold together the different colours of our lives, finds no spectrum for a brown-racist, devaluing character and is also a Christian image of the fact that for God this world should be as colourful, diverse and even flawed as we humans are (Genesis 9:17). As a church community, we have also reacted to the fact that the rainbow flag is no longer allowed to fly on masts that are the responsibility of Pirna&apos;s city council, as was the case in previous years.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>This is hard to bear and wrong in terms of content. The Protestant Church recognised and repented the mistakes made by parts of its institution during the years between 1933 and 1945. It acknowledged this in the Stuttgart Declaration of Guilt on 19 October 1945, in which it stated: ‘We accuse ourselves of not having confessed more courageously, prayed more faithfully, believed more cheerfully and loved more ardently.’</p>
<p> </p>
<p>We do not want to make this mistake again today and want to ‘boldly confess’ that openness and tolerance are part of our basic understanding. Already in the ‘Barmen Theological Declaration’ of 31 May 1934, deeply believing Christians opposed the terrible, evil and deadly exclusionary will of the Führer state. For many of them, such as Dietrich Bonhoeffer, this meant the death sentence.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>RELATED PAGES:</strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/business-against-far-right" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">German business against the far-right</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">Descendants of German resistance fighters</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">German mayors against the right</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">Germans against the far-right</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> |</span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><strong>IN YOUR OPINION:</strong></span><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> </span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;">Please comment</span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"> </span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>BACK TO TOP</strong></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[European Elections 2024]]></title><description><![CDATA[Pro-European parties retain a strong majority but German eurosceptic far-right makes gains]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/european-elections-2024</link><guid isPermaLink="false">666712106a6ddf959276996c</guid><category><![CDATA[Europe]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 15:09:51 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">EUROPEAN ELECTIONS 2024</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Pro-European parties retain a strong majority but right-wing parties make gains in Germany, Austria, France and Italy. Leftist parties win in Sweden, Denmark, Portugal and the Netherlands. Civic Coalition comes first in Poland</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_5d37445b040a4f6296b7c6f0917d4bb3~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="European Parliament in Strasburg"></figure>
<p>The European Parliament building, which opened in 1999, is named after Louse Weiss, a journalist, women&apos;s rights activist and, later in her life, Gaullist politician</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>June 2024:</strong> In the elections to the European Parliament in Strasbourg on 9 June 2024, pro-European party groups retained the majority despite suffering heavy losses in some cases. Out of 720 seats in parliament, staunchly pro-European party groups won 489 seats. However, they lost 36 seats. Eurosceptic groups won 131 seats, an increase of 13 seats. The 100 independents and non-defined members of parliament probably include a considerable number of Eurosceptics. For example, the 15 deputies sent to Strasbourg from the German far-right Alternative for Germany (AfD) belong to this group after the party was expelled from the Identity and Democracy grouping in the European Parliament.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In Germany, voter turnout was higher than ever after 16 and 17-year-olds were allowed to vote for the first time. Almost 65% of those eligible to vote cast their ballot. In the first all-German EU election in 1994, the turnout had been exactly 60 percent, in later votes only between 40 and 50 percent.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Around 65 million people in Germany were eligible to vote. The European elections are seen as a mood test for the German parties for the state elections in Saxony, Thuringia and Brandenburg in the autumn and for the parliamentary (Bundestag) elections in the autumn of next year.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p>Distribution of seats in the European Parliament</p>
<p><em>(by party groupings)</em></p>
<p><strong>Pro-European</strong></p>
<p>European People’s Party Group (EEP) centre-right – 185 seats (gained 9 seats)</p>
<p>Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats (S&amp;D), centre-left – 137 seats (lost 2 seats)</p>
<p>Renew Europe (RE), liberal / strongly pro-European – 79 seats (lost 23 seats)</p>
<p>Greens – European Free Alliance (Greens/EFA), 52 seats (lost 19 seats)</p>
<p>The Left in the European Parliament (GUE/NGL) 36 seats (lost 1 seat)</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Eurosceptic</strong></p>
<p>European Conservatives and Reformists, anti-federalists (ECR), 73 seats (gained 4 seats)</p>
<p>Identity and Democracy (ID), right-wing nationalists, 58 seats (gained 9 seats)</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Others</strong></p>
<p>Independents 46 seats (lost 16 seats)</p>
<p>Various others - 54 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Number of European Members of Parliament</p>
<p><em>(Country by country)</em></p>
<p>The number of Members of Parliament (MEPs) each country sends to Strasbourg (minimum six, maximum 96) depends on their population size. Small countries receive more seats in proportion to their population. The parliament has 720 seats in total:</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Germany: 96 | France: 81 | Italy: 76 | Spain: 61 | Poland: 53 | Romania: 33 | Netherlands: 31 | Belgium: 22 | Greece: 21 | Czech Republic: 21 | Sweden: 21 | Portugal: 21 | Hungary: 21 | Austria: 20 | Bulgaria: 17 | Denmark: 15 | Finland: 15 | Slovakia: 15  | Ireland: 14  | Croatia: 12  | Lithuania: 11  | Slovenia: 9  | Latvia: 9 | Estonia: 7 | Cyprus: 6 | Luxembourg: 6 | Malta: 6</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Results of 2024 European Elections</p>
<p><em>(Country-by-country results)</em></p>
<p><strong>AUSTRIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Freiheitliche Partei,</strong> right-wing, 25.7%, 6 seats, gained 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Österreichische Volkspartei,</strong> centre-right, 24.7%, 5 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Sozialdemokratische Partei</strong>, centre-left, 23.2%, 5 seats, no change</p>
<p><strong>Die Grünen</strong>, centre-left, green, 10.7%, 2 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>NEOS</strong>, liberal, 9.9%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>BELGIUM</strong></p>
<p><strong>Vlaams Belang</strong>, right-wing, 14.5%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>New Flemish Alliance</strong>, Flemish nationalist, 14.0%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Reformist Movement</strong>, liberal, 12.6%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Christian Democratic and Flemish</strong>, Christian-conservative, 8.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Vooruit</strong>, social-democratic, 8.0%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Socialist Party</strong>, socialist, 7.4%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Workers Party of Belgium</strong>, socialist, 5.1%, 1 seat, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Groen, Green</strong>, 6.3%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Open Flemish Liberals and Democrats</strong>, liberal, 5.6%, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Workers Party of Belgium</strong>, socialist, 5.6%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Les Engagés</strong>, French-speaking centrist party, 5.2%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>BULGARIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>GERB—SDS</strong>, centre-right, 23.5%, 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>Political Alliance PP–DB</strong>, pro-European, centre-left, 14.9%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Revival</strong>, far-right, 14.2%m 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>DPS (Movement for Rights and Freedom)</strong>, 13.5%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Bulgarian Socialist Party</strong>, centre-left, 7.1%, 2 seats, lost 3 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>CROATIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>HDZ (Croatian Democratic Union)</strong>, conservative, 34.6% 6 seats (gained 2 seats)</p>
<p><strong>SDP (Rivers of Justice)</strong>, centre-left, 26%, 4 seats</p>
<p><strong>Homeland Movement</strong>, nationalist, right-wing, 8.8%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Mozemo (We can)</strong>, leftist, green, 5.9%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>CYPRUS</strong></p>
<p><strong>Democratic Rally</strong>, Christian-democratic, 24.8%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>AKEK (Progressive party of Working People)</strong>, communist, 21.5%, 1 seat, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Fidias</strong>, 19.1%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>ELAM (National Popular Front)</strong> far-right, neo-fascist, 11.2%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>CZECH REPUBLIC</strong></p>
<p><strong>ANO</strong>, populist, 26.1%, 7 seats, gained 4 seats</p>
<p><strong>Spolu</strong>, centre-right, 22.3%, 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>AUTO</strong>, pro-motorists, 10.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Stacilo</strong>, left-wing, 9.6&amp;, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>STAN (Mayors for Europe)</strong>, centrist, 8.7%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Czech Pirate Party</strong>, liberal-progressive, 6.2%, 1 seat, lost 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>DENMARK</strong></p>
<p><strong>Green Left (SF)</strong>, 17.4%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Social Democrats</strong>, centre-left, 15.6%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Venstre</strong>, conservative, 14.7%, 2 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Liberal Alliance</strong>, centrist-liberal, 7%, 1 seat, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>ESTONIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Isamaa</strong>, Christian-democratic, 21.5%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Social Democratic Party</strong>, social-democratic, 19.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Estonian Reform Party</strong>, liberal, 17.9%, 1 seat, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Conservative People’s Party</strong>, right-wing, 14.9%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>FINLAND</strong></p>
<p><strong>National Coalition Party (KOK)</strong>, liberal, 24.8%, 4 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Left Alliance</strong>, socialist, 17.3%, 3 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Social Democratic Party</strong>, social-democratic, pro-European, 14.9%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Centre Party (KESK)</strong>, centrist, 11.6%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Green League</strong>, green, centre-left, 11.3%, 2 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>FRANCE</strong></p>
<p><strong>National Rally (RN)</strong>, far-right, 31.4%, 30 seats, gained 12 seats</p>
<p><strong>Besoin d’Europe</strong>, liberal, pro-European, 14.6%, 13 seats</p>
<p><strong>Réveiller L’Europe</strong>, socialist, 13.8%, 13 seats</p>
<p><strong>La France Insoumise</strong>, left-wing, 9.9%, 9 seats, gained 4 seats</p>
<p><strong>The Republicans</strong>, liberal-conservative, Gaullist, 7.3%, 6 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>The Ecologists (LE-EELV)</strong>, green, leftist, 5.5%, 5 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>La France Fière (Proud France)</strong>, 5.5%, 5 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>GERMANY</strong></p>
<p><strong>Christian Democrats (CDU)/CSU</strong>, centre-right, 30.0%, 29 seats</p>
<p><strong>Alternative for Germany (AfD)</strong>, far-right, 15.9%, 15 seats, gained 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>Social Democrats (SPD)</strong>, centre-left, 13.9%, 14 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>The Greens</strong>, centre-left, 11.9%, 12 seats, lost 9 seats</p>
<p><strong>Coalition Sahra Wagenknecht (BSW)</strong>, populist, 6.2%, 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>Free Democrats (FDP)</strong> centre-right, 5.2%, 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>The Left</strong>, leftist, 2.7%, 3 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Free Voters</strong>, centre-right, 2.7%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Volt Germany</strong>, pro-European, 2.6%, 3 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Die PARTEI</strong>, centrist, 1.9%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Tierschutzpartei</strong>, animal protection, 1.4%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>GREECE</strong></p>
<p>New Democracy, liberal-conservative, 28.3%, 7 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Syriza</strong>, leftist, 14.9%, 4 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>PASOK</strong>, social-democratic, 12.8%, 3 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Greek Solution</strong>, far-right, 9.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Communist Party of Greece</strong>, 9.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>HUNGARY</strong></p>
<p><strong>Fidesz</strong>, right-wing, 44.8%, 11 seats</p>
<p><strong>TISZA (Respect &amp; Freedom Party)</strong>, centre-left, 29.6%, 7 seats</p>
<p><strong>Dialogue Alliance</strong>, 8.1%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Our Homeland Movement</strong>, far-right, 6.7%, 1 seat, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>IRELAND</strong></p>
<p><strong>Fine Gael</strong>, liberal-conservative, 20.8%, 3 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Fianna Fáil</strong>, conservative, 20.4%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Sinn Féin</strong>, leftist, pro-united Ireland, 11.1%, 3 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>ITALY</strong></p>
<p><strong>Brothers of Italy,</strong> right-wing, 28.8%, 24 seats, gained 14 seats</p>
<p><strong>Democratic Party</strong>, centre-left, 24.1%, 21 seats, gained 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>Five Star Movement</strong>, populist, 10.0%, 8 seats, gained 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Forzo Italia</strong>, centre-right, 9.6%, 8 seats</p>
<p><strong>Lega</strong>, right-wing, 9.0%, 8 seats, lost 14 seats</p>
<p><strong>AVS (Greens)</strong>, leftist, 6.8%, 6 seats, gained 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>South Tyrolian People’s Party</strong>, conservative, 0.5%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>LATVIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>New Unity</strong>, centre-right, 25.1%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>National Alliance</strong>, right-wing, populist, 22.1%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>For Latvia’s Development (LA)</strong>, 9.4%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>The Progressives</strong>, social-democratic, 7.4%, 1 seat, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>LITHUANIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Homeland Union</strong>, conservative, 21.3%, 3 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Social Democratic Party</strong>, centre-left, 18.0%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Lithuanian Farmers</strong>, green-conservative, 9.1%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>People &amp; Justice Union</strong>, centrist, 5.5%, 1 seat, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>LUXEMBOURG</strong></p>
<p><strong>Christian Social People’s Party (CSV)</strong>, conservative, 22.9%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Luxembourg Socialist workers’ Party (LSAP)</strong>, social-democratic, 21.7%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Democratic Party</strong>, liberal, 18.3%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Alternative Democratic Reform Party (ADR)</strong>, conservative, 11.3%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>MALTA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Labour Party</strong>, centre-left, 45.3%, 3 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Nationalist Party</strong>, conservative, 42.0%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>NETHERLANDS</strong></p>
<p><strong>GroenLinks–PvdA</strong>, green, centre-left, 21.6%, 8 seats</p>
<p><strong>Party for Freedom (PVV)</strong>, right-wing, populist, 17.7%, 6 seats, gained 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>People’s Party (VVD)</strong>, centre-right, 11.6%, 4 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Christian Democratic Appeal (CDA)</strong>, centre-right, 9.7%, 3 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Democrats 66</strong>, centrist-liberal, 8.1%, 3 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Vold Netherlands</strong>, liberal, strongly pro-European, 4.9%, 2 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Farmer-Citizen Movement (BBB)</strong>, right-wing, 5.3%, 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>POLAND</strong></p>
<p><strong>Civic Coalition (KO)</strong>, centrist, 37.1%, 21 seats</p>
<p><strong>Law and Justice (PiS)</strong>, right-wing populist, 36.2%, 20 seats, lost 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>Confederation</strong>, far-right, 12.1%, 6 seats, gained 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>Third Way (Trzecia Droga)</strong>, centre-right, 6.9%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>The Left</strong> (Lewica), leftist, 6.3%, 3 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>PORTUGAL</strong></p>
<p><strong>Socialist Party</strong>, social-democratic, 32.1%, 8 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Democratic Alliance (AD)</strong>, centre-right, 31.1%, 7 seats</p>
<p><strong>Chega</strong>, right-wing, 9.8%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Liberal Initiative (IL)</strong>, liberal, 9.1%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Left Bloc (BE)</strong>, left-wing, 4.3%, 1 seat, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>CDU (Unitary Democratic Coalition)</strong>, left-wing green, 4.1%, 1 seat, lost 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>ROMANIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>National Coalition for Romania</strong>, centre-left, 48.7%, 19 seats</p>
<p><strong>Alliance for the Union of Romanians</strong>, right-wing, 14.9%, 6 seats, gained 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>United Right Alliance</strong>, centre-right, 8.6%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Democratic Alliance of Hungarians</strong>, represents the Hungarian minority, 6.6%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>SOS Romania</strong>, far right, 5%, 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>SLOVAKIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Progressive Slovakia (PS)</strong>, liberal, 27.8%, 6 seats</p>
<p><strong>Social Democracy (SMER)</strong>, left-wing nationalist, 24.6%, 5 seats, gained 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Republika</strong>, far-right, 12.5%, 2 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Voice – Social Democracy (HLAS)</strong>, social-democratic, 7.2%, 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>SLOVENIA</strong></p>
<p><strong>Slovenian Democratic Party (SDS)</strong>, conservative, 30.7%, 4 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Freedom Movement (Z.DEJ)</strong>, liberal green, 22.2%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Vesna - Green Party</strong>, green, 10.5%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Social Democrat (SD),</strong> centre-left pro-European, 7.7%, 1 seat, lost 1 seat</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>SPAIN</strong></p>
<p><strong>People’s Party (PP)</strong>, conservative, 34.2%, 22 seats, gained 9 seats</p>
<p><strong>Spanish Socialist Workers’ Party</strong>, social-democratic, 30.2%, 20 seats, lost 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>VOX</strong>, right-wing, 9.6%, 6 seats, gained 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Republics Now,</strong> centre-left, 4.9%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>SUMAR</strong>, left-wing, 4.7%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>SALF</strong>, liberal, 4.6%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Podemos</strong>, left-wing populist, 3.3%, 2 seats, lost 2 seats</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>SWEDEN</strong></p>
<p><strong>Social Democratic Party</strong>, centre-left, 24.8%, 5 seats</p>
<p><strong>Moderate Party</strong>, conservative, 17.6%, 4 seats</p>
<p><strong>Green Party</strong>, green, 13.8%, 3 seats</p>
<p><strong>Sweden Democrats</strong>, right-wing populist, 13.2%, 3 seats, gained 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Left Party</strong>, socialist, 11%, 2 seats</p>
<p><strong>Centre Party</strong>, liberal, 7.3%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Christian Democrats</strong>, centre-right, 5.7%, 1 seat</p>
<p><strong>Liberals</strong>, liberal, 4.4%, 1 seat</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>________________________</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>On other pages: </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/quo-vadis-herbert-kickl" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Austrian 2024 general election</a></strong><strong> | </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/afd-eastern-germany" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Alternative for Germany (AfD) in eastern Germany</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to their fellow citizens to reject the New Right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German campaign against the far-right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" target="_blank">Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> </span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank">Please comment</a></span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[German Constitution]]></title><description><![CDATA[Germany celebrates its post-war constitution and discusses strengthening judicial independence. Germany's post-war constitution or basic law]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-constitution</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66508773ceadafb68aeba541</guid><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><category><![CDATA[History]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 12:46:06 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">Germany celebrates its post-war constitution and discusses strengthening judicial independence</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Germany&apos;s post-war constitution or basic law (Grundgesetz) has been in force since 23 May 1949</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_a1227095dd7344b994c913ad33f5483a~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="German constitution"></figure>
<p>Germany’s post-war constitution (Grundgesetz) was signed by Konrad Adenauer (Christian Democrat), Adolph Schönfelder (Social Democrat) and Hermann Schäfer (Liberal). Adenauer was later to become West Germany’s first Chancellor</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>May 2024:</strong> Some 75 years ago, on 23 May 1949, the German post-war constitution, the Basic Law (Grundgesetz), came into force. Drawn up by the Parliamentary Council consisting of 70 people - 66 men and four women - the constitutional document was only legally valid in the then federal states of West Germany, consisting of the occupation zones (Besatzungszonen) of the US, France and Great Britain (1).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Gundgesetz was intended as a provisional measure and was to be replaced by an all-German constitution after the eventual reunification of West and East Germany. However, this did not happen. After the fall of the East German regime, in the German Democratic Republic (GDR) the desire for rapid unification was greater than constitutional considerations. On 23 August 1990, the first freely elected GDR parliament (Volkskammer) decided to join the West German Basic Law. The Grundgesetz has therefore been in force throughout Germany since 3 October 1990.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>On 1 September 1948, the so-called ‘Parliamentary Council’ convened in Bonn. It consisted of members from the federal state parliaments and representatives from West Berlin (1). Their task was to draw up a constitution for the post-war German republic. The guiding principle was to avoid all the mistakes of the Weimar Republic (2) which had contributed to the downfall of German democracy after World War I. Crimes as atrocious as those committed by Germany under the Nazis should never again be possible.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Chairman of the Parliamentary Council was the later German Federal Chancellor (Bundeskanzler) Konrad Adenauer.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The members of the Parliamentary Council discussed for almost nine months to agree on a joint draft. Exactly four years after the end of the Second World War, on 8 May 1949, the Parliamentary Council adopted the Basic Law. In the following days, the constitution for the Federal Republic of Germany (Bundesrepublik Deutschland) was approved by eleven of the twelve state parliaments and by representatives of the US, France and Great Britain.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Grundgesetz enshrines several basic rights that guarantee citizens fundamental freedoms and protection. These rights in Articles 1 to 19 include the inviolability of human dignity, personal freedom, freedom of expression, freedom of the press and information, freedom of assembly, freedom of association, freedom of faith, conscience and religion, freedom of movement, freedom to choose an occupation, the right to property and the right of inheritance.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>This historical development can also be seen in how the Basic Law is structured. The fundamental rights are deliberately placed at the front of the constitutional text, unlike in the Weimar (2) constitution. A perpetuity clause safeguards the principles of constitutional law: human dignity, democracy, the rule of law, the federal state and the welfare state. They may not be abolished even with a two-thirds majority in the Bundestag and Bundesrat (Lower and Upper houses of the German parliament).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Grundgesetz was proclaimed on 23 May 1949 by West Germany’s first Federal Chancellor Konrad Adenauer. It then came into force in the former West German federal states (Bundesländer). It became the constitution of the Federal Republic of Germany (Bundesrepublik Deutschland) and has been the constitution of reunified Germany since 3 October 1990. The Basic Law has been amended many times. Given possible extremist majorities, there is currently a debate on how the independence of the Federal Constitutional Court (Bundesverfassungsgericht) - as the guarantor of fundamental rights - can be enshrined in the Basic Law.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>(1) The Grundgesetz (Basic Law) initially applied in the West German states of Baden, Bavaria, Bremen, Greater Berlin, Hamburg, Hesse, Lower Saxony, North Rhine-Westphalia, Rhineland-Palatinate, Schleswig-Holstein, Württemberg-Baden and Württemberg-Hohenzollern, which existed in 1949. It was to come into force in the areas of the Soviet zone after German reunification.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>(2) The Weimar Republic is the name given to the German government between the end of the Imperial period (1918) and the beginning of Nazi Germany (1933). The Weimar Republic draws its name from the town of Weimar in Thuringia where the constitutional assembly met.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em><strong>Sources: </strong></em><em>Bundestag (German Federal Parliament), Bundesregierung (German Federal Government), ARD (German National Broadcaster)</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES:   </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank"><strong>Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</strong></a><strong> | </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer"><strong>Anti far-right demos in Berlin and hundreds of other German towns and cities</strong></a><strong>  |  </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>Descendants of German Nazi resistance fighters against the far-right</strong></a><strong> | </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><strong>German mayor against the far-right</strong></a><strong> |</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank"><strong>Please comment</strong></a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[German Business Women-2]]></title><description><![CDATA[Ageing baby boomers provide openings for women to advance to senior roles in business]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-business-women-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">663dfa656bdcea759a369462</guid><category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category><category><![CDATA[Women]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 11:02:09 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">GERMAN BUSINESS WOMEN</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Ageing baby boomers provide openings for women to advance to senior roles in business</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_7103e9396f6a4f8b99c50718b79ba959~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p>Simone Bagel-Trah head of the supervisory board of Henkel. Henkel AG<strong> </strong>is a German multinational chemical and consumer goods company headquartered in Düsseldorf, Germany. Founded in 1876, the company, listed on the German DAX share index, is organised into two globally operating business units (Consumer Brands, Adhesive Technologies) and is known for brands such as Loctite, Persil, Pritt, Fa, Dial and Purex. The company employs some 48,000 people worldwide.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>May 2024: </strong>Very few women make it to the top levels of German family-owned businesses, says a new study by the non-profit Allbright Foundation. The proportion of female managers in the 100 family-owned companies with the highest turnover stands at just 12.6 per cent. Although the proportion of women has increased by four percentage points since the last survey two years ago, it remains significantly below that of the 160 companies listed on the German stock exchanges, where it averages 19 per cent. Some 46 per cent of German companies with a turnover of more than 50 million euros are family-owned businesses.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“It is high time to promote women to leading management positions if family-owned businesses want to remain attractive employers,” the study’s authors commented.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Companies like Aldi, Lidl, Bertelsmann, Bosch, Porsche, Henkel, Miele, Oetker and Otto, the best-known German global family businesses, shape the country’s economy. Now the baby boomer generation is about to retire from the companies and almost half of family businesses face a generational change. The 100 largest family-owned companies have long struggled with women in management, but now there is some movement: At 12.6 per cent, the proportion of women is still very low, but the generational change offers an opportunity to modernise management structures quickly. However, some companies are already showing how it can be done.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The greater the influence of non-family shareholders in companies, the higher the proportion of women on the management boards. Some 20 of the 100 largest German family-owned companies are also listed on the Frankfurt stock exchanges (DAX, MDAX, SDAX) with family members holding a significant proportion of the shares (e.g. BMW, Continental, Henkel or Merck). At just below 20 per cent, the proportion of women on the management boards of these companies corresponds roughly to the average for all listed companies and is therefore significantly higher than for non-listed family-oned companies (10.6%).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Powerful positions such as the chairmanships of the management or the supervisory boards are still predominantly entrusted to men from within the share-owning families. Only two of the large family businesses have female family members as CEOs: Anna Maria Braun at B. Braun Melsungen and Nicola Leibinger-Kammüller at Trumpf. Since March 2020, not a single woman from a business family has joined a management board. There are only three women in the chair of supervisory boards: Cathrina Claas-Mühlhäuser (Claas), Simone Bagel-Trah (Henkel) and Bettina Würth (Würth).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to separate research by the Family Business Foundation (Stiftung Familienunternehmen), some 90 per cent of all German companies are family-controlled businesses. They generate 55 per cent of national turnover and account for around 57 per cent of all employment. The Family Business Foundation points out that the German economy is characterised by many more large family businesses compared to other industrial nations. Some 46 per cent of companies with a turnover of more than 50 million euros are family-owned businesses.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/women-board-members" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">DAX Women</span></a></u><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/women-remain-behind" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">Angela Merkel effect</span></a></u><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-women-mayors" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">German Women Mayors</span></a></u><span style="color: #d21111;"> |</span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>I<strong>N YOUR OPINION: </strong><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;">Please commen</span></a></u><span style="color: #d21111;">t</span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Swiss Climate Seniors]]></title><description><![CDATA[Top European Court hands Swiss women wide-ranging climate victory]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/swiss-climate-seniors</link><guid isPermaLink="false">661817a327f16e0b5178bbbe</guid><category><![CDATA[Environment]]></category><category><![CDATA[Women]]></category><category><![CDATA[Europe]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 17:23:57 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">EUROPEAN COURT OF HUMAN RIGHTS</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Top European Court hands Swiss women wide-ranging climate victory</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_a526903662ba4eaaab7d24da850cfdb6~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Swiss climate women celebrate their victory in Strasbourg"></figure>
<p>Members of the Swiss Climate Seniors (KlimaSeniorinnen) celebrate their victory in the European Court of Human Rights</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>April 2024: </strong>A determined group of senior Swiss women won a great victory against its own country in the European Court of Human Rights (ECHR). Switzerland must do more to protect the climate, according to the judges in the case brought by the climate seniors. Europe&apos;s top human rights court ruled that the Swiss government had violated the human rights of its citizens by failing to do enough to combat climate change. The decision is likely to be used as a precedent in future climate lawsuits.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Court’s unprecedented ruling, in favour of the more than 2,500 Swiss women (KlimaSeniorinnen), who brought the case, is expected to resonate in court decisions across Europe and beyond and to embolden more communities to bring climate cases against governments.<span style="color: black;">. This is the first time that the ECHR has condemned a state for failing to take action against climate change, linking the protection of human rights to compliance with environmental obligations.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p>The ECHR pointed out that there was sufficient evidence that climate change posed a &quot;serious present and future threat&quot; to the exercise of ECHR rights. The states are aware of this and are also in a position to take measures to effectively counter this threat. If it is possible to limit the rise in temperature to 1.5 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels, the risks are likely to be lower. The legal obligations of states under the ECHR are limited to people living at the moment. Nevertheless, future generations will be particularly affected by climate change.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In her ruling, ECHR President Siofra O&apos;Leary said the Swiss government had failed to comply with its targets for cutting greenhouse gas emissions and had failed to set a national carbon budget. &quot;It is clear that future generations are likely to bear an increasingly severe burden of the consequences of present failures and omissions to combat climate change,&quot; O&apos;Leary said.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>One of KlimaSeniorinnen&apos;s leaders, Rosmarie Wydler-Wälti, said she was struggling to grasp the full extent of the decision. “Today is a day of joy, relief and very strong emotions,” said Norma Bargetzi-Horisberger, another member of the group.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The legal complaint by the <em>KlimaSeniorinnen</em> stated that the Swiss authorities have failed to act on climate change. “Climate change hurts people’s living conditions and health.” The women argued that Switzerland has not fulfilled its obligations under Articles 2 and 8 of the Convention on Human Rights (4). Article 2 refers to people’s ‘Right to Life’, while Article 8 deals with protecting people’s privacy and family life. The climate seniors also maintain that they were declined access to Swiss courts.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The Swiss climate activists used women&apos;s vulnerability to back up their lawsuit. The case against Switzerland before the European Court of Human Rights is the first climate lawsuit at the European level. The ruling in favour of the climate seniors could be used as a precedent in future legal challenges against the climate policies of all or any of the 46 member states of the Council of Europe.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The ECHR also ruled on two other cases. It ruled that the case brought by a group of young Portuguese against Portugal and 32 other countries, including Germany and Switzerland, was inadmissible. It drew the same conclusion as the legal action brought <span style="color: black;">by Damien Carême, the</span> former mayor of the French municipality of Grande-Synthe, who asked to condemn the French government for climate inaction.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In a statement, the environmental campaigning network Greenpeace commented: “This is a huge victory not only for all the older women but for access to justice across Europe. Switzerland must now adjust its current climate targets based on science. The Court found that Switzerland had failed to comply with its duties under the Convention concerning climate change. The Swiss authorities had not acted in time and in an appropriate way to implement measures to mitigate the effects of climate change in this case. Furthermore, Switzerland has not achieved its inadequate targets for reducing greenhouse gas emissions. For the first time, a transnational court specialising in human rights is directly upholding a human rights-based right to climate protection.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>This ruling could have far-reaching implications. It sets a precedent for all 46 states of the Council of Europe. Across Europe, all Council of Europe states could be asked by their citizens to review and, if necessary, strengthen their climate policy based on the principles developed by the ECHR to safeguard human rights. This would benefit everyone – young and old. This ruling sends out a global signal.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;This judgement is not just a victory for the Senior Women for Climate Protection. Our victory is a victory for all generations. Especially for the Portuguese youth, whose generation will be beneficiaries of a long-term improved climate. The presence of the young people in the courtroom showed the judges the face of human rights for the future,&quot; says Rosemarie Wydler-Wälti, Co-President of the Swiss Senior Women for Climate Protection.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;This ruling is a landmark in the struggle for a liveable climate for everyone. And the ruling is a satisfaction. We have been fighting for climate justice for nine years with the support of Greenpeace. After the Swiss courts refused to hear us, the ECHR has now confirmed that climate protection is a human right,&quot; says Anne Mahrer, Co-President of the Swiss Senior Women for Climate Protection.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;I am overwhelmed and extremely proud that after 9 years of intensive work, the senior women have finally got their due. This is an indescribable moment,&quot; says Cordelia Bähr, lead lawyer for the Swiss Senior Women for Climate Protection. &quot;The significance of this decision cannot be overestimated. It will be of great importance for further climate lawsuits against states and companies worldwide and increase their chances of success. The judgment shows citizens, judges and governments across Europe what is needed in terms of climate protection to respect human rights.&quot;</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>On other pages: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/women-vs-switzerland" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Women fighting climate change</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/city-trees" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Street trees in German cities</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/climate-goals" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>German climate goals </strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> </strong></span></p>
<p><strong>In your opinion: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Please comment</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> </strong></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Notes</strong></p>
<p><strong>1)</strong> KlimaSeniorinnen was founded in August 2016 by some 150 senior women. The group has now more than 2,300 members in addition to some 1,000 supporters. Because older women are most affected by the more frequent and more intense heatwaves, membership, on the advice of their lawyers, is restricted to older women. The average age of members is currently 73.</p>
<p><strong>2)</strong> The Paris Climate Accords, is an international treaty on climate change. Adopted in 2015, the agreement covers climate change mitigation, adaptation, and finance.</p>
<p><strong>3)</strong> The European Court of Human Rights (EctHR) was set up in 1959. It hears applications alleging that a contracting state has breached one or more of the human rights provisions concerning civil and political rights set out in the European Convention on Human Rights.</p>
<p><strong>4)</strong> The European Convention on Human Rights (ECHR) protects the human rights of people in countries that belong to the Council of Europe. All 47 Member States of the Council, including the UK, have signed the Convention. Its full title is the ‘Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms’.</p>
<p><strong>5)</strong> The Council of Europe was founded after the Second World War to protect human rights and the rule of law, and to promote democracy. The Member States’ first task was to draw up a treaty to secure basic rights for anyone within their borders, including their own citizens and people of other nationalities.</p>
<p><strong>6)</strong> Damien Carême was shortlisted for the <a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/contest_2016/world-mayor-shortlist-2016.html" target="_blank"><span style="color: rgb(174, 80, 80);">2016 World Mayor Prize</span></a><span style="color: rgb(174, 80, 80);"> </span></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ukrainian Refugees]]></title><description><![CDATA[Half of Ukrainian refugees in Germany want to remain]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/ukrainian-refugees</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66101d7a41cdaa40ad3add8c</guid><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><category><![CDATA[Europe]]></category><category><![CDATA[Immigration]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 16:05:40 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">Half of Ukrainian refugees</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">want to remain in Germany</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_608590d6fd8e4f0abee5dbb573e60952~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Ukrainian refugees in Germany"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Since the beginning of the Russian invasion of Ukraine in February 2022, more than one million people have fled from the war-torn country to Germany, most of them being women and children. Research carried out this year indicates that nearly half of the refugees would like to remain in Germany for at least several years or even forever. Even of those who do not want to stay in Germany forever, some 30 per cent hope to be able to maintain close contact with Germany and perhaps live intermittently in the country.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The family situation and social integration play a major role for the refugees` intentions to stay. Refugees who fled without their partners are more likely to want to return to their home country. On the other hand, refugees who are looking for education or training opportunities, those who have a good knowledge of German and those who feel welcome in the country are more likely to want to stay forever.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The findings are part of research that was carried earlier this year and involved questioning some 6,500 Ukrainian refugees. The research was carried out by the Institute of Applied Social Science (Infas) and funded by the German government.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Learning German</strong></p>
<p>There has been substantial progress in German language learning. Three out of four Ukrainian refugees attended or completed one or more German courses by early 2023, most often combined language and integration teaching. Refugees’ self-assessment of their German language skills has improved since the late summer of 2022. While only few refugees (8 per cent) rate their German proficiency as “good” or “very good”, more than 27 per cent rate their German as “okay” (compared to 14 per cent in mid-2022). The proportion of refugees who claim to know no German has than halved to 18 per cent.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Since a large part of the refugees were still participating in integration courses when the research was carried out, the share of those who have finished with degrees should have increased in the meantime. Visiting additional language courses as well as exchanges in private and the future professional life should improve German skills even further.</p>
<p>​</p>
<p><strong>Employment</strong></p>
<p>Due to the time taken up by language and integration courses, the employment rate among Ukrainians has only increased slightly. In the summer of 2022, some 17 per cent of 18 to 64-year-olds were employed. Nine months later, the figure stood at 18 per cent. But even moderate language proficiency will improve labour market opportunities for many refugees. Indeed, more than two-thirds of Ukrainians, who were not employed at the beginning of 2023, wanted to start work immediately or within months.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Children</strong></p>
<p>Children and adolescents make up a significant proportion of the refugees: About every second Ukrainian woman has come to Germany with at least one child. Almost half of these children are under the age of ten. Most children and adolescents, according to their parents, have a “good” or “very good” general health.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>While almost all school-aged children from Ukraine attend a general or vocational school, only a few parents make use of daycare facilities. Only half of children aged, six years or younger, were attending childcare outside the home at the beginning of 2023. The research authors comment that the supply of enough daycare places is important for parents to be able to attend language courses and to take up employment – and for children to learn the language, to have a structured everyday life</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>The survey’s authors also stress that the government must quickly decide on the extension of temporary protection of Ukrainian refugees beyond March 2024 or to create other long-term residence prospects. “Investment in social participation and employment requires planning and legal certainty as well as reliable residence prospects – both for refugees themselves and for the German society at large,” the researchers conclude.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><u><span style="color: #000000;"><a href="#foo" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></span></u></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>On other pages:</strong> <u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/eu-asylum" rel="noreferrer"><span style="color: #000000;">European immigration and asylum</span></a></u> |</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>German Brief&apos;s news pages:</strong> <u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/brief-german-news"><span style="color: #000000;">News in brief</span></a></u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/brief-german-news"><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></a><span style="color: #000000;">| </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/in-depth-news"><span style="color: #000000;">News in depth</span></a></u><span style="color: #000000;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-politics"><span style="color: #000000;">Politics</span></a></u><span style="color: #000000;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-business-news"><span style="color: #000000;">Business &amp; Finance</span></a></u><span style="color: #000000;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-sports-news"><span style="color: #000000;">Sport</span></a></u><span style="color: #000000;"> | </span><u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-weather"><span style="color: #000000;">Weather</span></a></u><span style="color: #000000;"> |   </span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>In your opinion:</strong> <u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments"><span style="color: #000000;">Please comment</span></a></u></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(139, 0, 0);">​</span></p>
<p><strong>Contributing news stories</strong></p>
<p>Please email the <u><a href="mailto:german.brief.org@gmail.com?subject=Editor"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>German Brief Editor</strong></span></a></u><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"> </span> if you wish to suggest or contribute a news story. Alternatively, you may use our <u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments"><span style="color: #000000;">input form</span></a></u><u><span style="color: #000000;">.</span></u></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Christian Streich Freiburg]]></title><description><![CDATA[Christian Streich (SC Freiburg), the Bundeliga's best-loved manager is stepping down]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/christian-streich-freiburg</link><guid isPermaLink="false">660044a8de910f4fadba1ece</guid><category><![CDATA[Sport]]></category><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 15:55:39 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Christian Streich, SC Freiburg, steps down</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Julian Schuster appointed new head coach</strong></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_13a5b0f874d14aa798d99a67f1782a27~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="SC Freiburg's head coach Christian Streich steps down after more then 12 years"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Tears flowed as Freiburg said goodbye to football coach Christian Streich</strong></p>
<p><strong>11 May 2024: </strong>The 1:1 draw against Heidenheim was Christian Streich&apos;s last home game as head coach of the SC Freiburg. After the game, tens of thousands of supporters celebrated him with a lap of honour through the stadium. Players and fans described it as a well-deserved farewell.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Even half an hour after the final whistle, the Freiburg stadium was still full. None of the spectators had left their seats. Even the visiting fans from Heidenheim had stayed to see Christian Streich off after his last home game as coach of the Sport Club. Chants of &quot;Christian Streich, you are the best man&quot; echoed through the arena and the &quot;legend&quot; did a lap of honour to say goodbye. Streich waved, kissed hands and bowed to the fans. &quot;I was in tears when I saw that,&quot; said one SC supporter after the game.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;It was just completely emotional,&quot; said another fan, &quot;when you look at the last twelve and a half years and everything we&apos;ve been through - 2nd division, promotion, Europa League, Turin, London. I&apos;m completely lost for words. But nothing you do is worthy of Christian&quot;.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The farewell to their coach was also &quot;very emotional&quot; for the players. &quot;The whole stadium was full, people stayed and shouted his name. I think that was the recognition he deserved for the work he has done for the club,&quot; said Freiburg captain Christian Günter, who would have liked to have given Streich a win as a farewell present. &quot;We tried to throw everything into it. Unfortunately, it wasn&apos;t enough, but it was still a fitting farewell for him,&quot; said the 31-year-old.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The fans also expressed their appreciation for Streich with many posters. &quot;Thank you Christian SC legend&quot; and &quot;Loyalty and honesty unfortunately a rarity. Take care Christian&quot; could be read on them. In the subsequent press conference, Streich thanked the supporters for all the applause and &quot;a good relationship over so many years&quot;.</p>
<p><em>Source: SWR Sport</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>The Bundesliga’s best-loved football coach is stepping down</strong></p>
<p><strong>March 2024: </strong>Christian Streich, the football head coach of Bundesliga club SC Freiburg, told the club’s fans in an emotional video that he would be stepping down at the end of the 2023/24 season, after more than 12 years at the helm. He said that the time was right to step aside.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“I’d like to share with you, with a very heavy heart, that I will not be continuing in my role as head coach of my beloved SC Freiburg this summer. I thought long and hard, but I believe it is the right time after 29 years to allow in new people, new energy, and new possibilities at the SC. I also believe our players and the people around us will need that new energy. It’s always been important to me that I don’t miss the moment when I believe it is time to go.”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>_________________</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong><span style="color: #2c20bc;">Quotes from Christian Streich</span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;">“The god of money is getting bigger and bigger, at some point it will devour everything.&quot;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;">&quot;I may have a German passport, but I don&apos;t feel German. I am a human being who has a passport that says German in it.&quot;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;">&quot;My players are being offered like cattle on a market. You can read their release clause in the newspapers - it&apos;s terrible.&quot;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;">&quot;Go and vote! So that we can gather votes against these unspeakable, xenophobic and unwelcoming policies of some political parties.&quot;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;">&quot;We don&apos;t have to make ourselves any sexier than we are, but we&apos;re not completely unsexy. Well, I&apos;m relatively unsexy now, I admit that. But the club is admittedly a bit sexy.&quot;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #2c20bc;"> </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><span style="color: #2c20bc;">Source: Badische Zeitung, Freiburg</span></em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>_________________</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Freiburg’s Director of Sport Jochen Saier added: “Over the past few weeks, we have had an intensive, very trusting and emotional exchange of ideas with Christian - which has resulted in a decision that we regret, but which we can fully respect and understand. Christian&apos;s work over the past 12 and a half years as head coach and almost three decades of coaching for our club was and is as special as the joint decision-making process.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>As a former player and later youth coach at the Black Forest club for 15 years, Streich became assistant to first-team coach Marcus Sorg at the start of the 2011/12 season. He then became head coach on 1 January 2012 and has guided the team to its most successful era.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Streich led the team to fifth in his first full season in charge, while the club stuck with him when relegated in 2015. He led them straight back up, topping the second Bundesliga table ahead of RB Leipzig and helped stabilise Freiburg as a top-flight side.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Last year he also led the Black Forest outfit to fifth with a club record of 59 points, ensuring back-to-back campaigns of European football for the first time in their history. Those UEFA Europa League journeys both ended in the knockout stages against Juventus and West Ham United.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>The previous season he took Freiburg to the club’s first DFB Cup final, losing unluckily on penalties to Leipzig. Last season, it was again <em>Leipzig</em> that knocked the Freiburg side out in the semi-finals of the Cup.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>At the time of his announcement, Christian Streich had been in the job for 4,463 days, ranking him fifth among the longest-serving coaches of a Bundesliga club. None of the other 17 coaches in the division have overseen as many fixtures as him in the German top flight of football. During his years as Bundesliga manager, the SC Freiburg played 383 matches, winning 133, drawing 109 and losing 141</p>
<p> </p>
<p>However, it isn’t just Streich’s exploits as a football coach that will ensure that his legacy is never forgotten. The Baden-Württemberg native would rarely shy away from a comment about politics or social issues, speaking in his trademark local dialect that many Germans struggle with.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In 2023, Streich was awarded the Julius Hirsch Prize for his clear stance against xenophobia, racism and discrimination: &quot;With his consistently authentic statements, he not only calls for civil courage but is himself a role model for it,&quot; it said in the citation.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“This club has been my life and I’m extraordinarily grateful for the support and affection I’ve received. I’m full of gratitude that I experienced it all. I’d like to thank you all. I’m excited about the future of this club. A great club, a great time for me, but it’s the right time for me to say goodbye,” Christian Streich said.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Julian Schuster to take over from Christian Streich</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_af19b1c28cd941528857a957c8a997ec~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: black;">April 2024:</span></strong><span style="color: black;"> After the departure of Christian Streich, Julian Schuster will take over the position of SC Freiburg’s head coach next season, with Patrik Grolimund joining the coaching staff as his assistant.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: black;"> </span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: black;">Julian Schuster arrived at the SC Freiburg in the 2008/09 season as a player and made 242 competitive appearances for the club over the next ten years. He was named as club captain during the winter break of the 2011/12 season and led the line for SC up until his retirement in 2018. Schuster was appointed as coordinator of talent management at the club in July 2018 and worked with the Freiburg Football School, U23 and the senior squad to integrate youth talent into the first team. Schuster was also active as an assistant coach at this time. This year, Schuster acquired his UEFA Pro License, the highest coaching badge in German football.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>Sources: Deutscher Fußball-Bund (German Football Association), SC Freiburg and others.</em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>BACK TO TOP</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES:</strong> <span style="color: #D21111;">German Football | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-football-index" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Germans Football Index</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/juergen-klopp-joins-red-bull" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German football legend koins Red Bull</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> |</span></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION:</strong> <span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Please comment</a></span><u><span style="color: #D21111;"> </span></u>| </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Buergermeister gegen Rechts]]></title><description><![CDATA[German mayors against the right. “The ideology of the far-right makes me want to vomit.”]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts</link><guid isPermaLink="false">65ccb9830bf7e931afacfd48</guid><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 13:26:17 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>German mayors against the right</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Bürgermeister gegen Rechts</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&gt; Hamburg Mayor: </strong>“There is no place for racism in Hamburg.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&gt; Leipzig Mayor:</strong> “The ideology of the far-right makes me want to vomit.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&gt; Munich Mayor:</strong> “When tens of thousands of my fellow citizens speak out against racism and hate, I am proud to be their mayor.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&gt; Stuttgart Mayor: </strong>“Right-wing extremist movements are trying to undermine our basic democratic order.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&gt; Havixbeck Mayor:</strong> “I am very worried about the threat to our democracy.”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_c66540eb76244faeb451410d548cb25e~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_555,h_555,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_e7de43d6c4c248b3b34eea1a297da380~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_8f5dd959b37441bdbc645d166c3e92a7~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p>German mayors against the Right (from left): Eliza Diekmann (Coesfeld, North Rhine-Westphalia), Peter Tschentscher (Hamburg), Gabriele Zull (Fellbach, Baden-Württemberg)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>The largest protest movement in post-war Germany</strong></p>
<p><strong>February 2024:</strong> Since mid-January 2024, millions of Germans have taken part in demonstrations against right-wing extremist parties, groups and their ideologies. The people came from all parts of Germany. They were old and they were young. Hundreds of thousands protested in Hamburg and Berlin. But citizens have also come together in small towns in the Erzgebirge (Ore Mountains), the Schwarzwald (Black Forest) and on the Schäbische Alp (Swabian Alp) to take a stand against the New Right and its hatred. Weekly protests have taken place in medieval towns in West and East Germany where citizens met under the slogan &apos;Never again&apos;. Never again should Nazi ideology gain a foothold in Germany.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The wave of protest that is now sweeping across the German states from the coasts in the North to the Alps in the South is the largest in post-war Germany.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><span style="color: black;">The trigger to the current wave of protests against right-wing extremism in Germany was a meeting between far-right propagandists and politicians from the AfD party (Alternative for Germany) and the Werteunion, the rightist wing of Germany’s main opposition party the CDU (Christian Democratic Union) in a villa in Potsdam, south of Berlin.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: black;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="color: black;">The media outlet ‘Correctiv’ made the Potsdam meeting public. The meeting’s agenda centred around the idea of re-migration, a term used by right-wing extremists when they discuss large-scale deportation of people of foreign origin, if necessary, by force. At times, AfD politicians have also used the term.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: black;"> </span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>German President Frank-Walter Steinmeier</strong></p>
<p>All political parties represented in the German National Parliament (Bundestag), except the far-right AfD, strongly support the protests. German President Frank-Walter Steinmeier has thanked the millions of demonstrators against right-wing extremism for their commitment to democracy. &quot;These people give us all courage. They defend our republic and our Basic Law (German constitution) against its enemies. They are defending our humanity,&quot; he said in Berlin.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>German Chancellor Olaf Scholz</strong></p>
<p>German Chancellor Olaf Scholz took part in a demonstration at his home in Potsdam. &quot;What we are currently experiencing here in our country concerns us all - every one of us,&quot; emphasised Scholz. &quot;I will say it clearly and harshly: right-wing extremists are attacking our democracy. They want to destroy our cohesion.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Parliamentary opposition leader Friedrich Merz from the centre-right Christian Democrats (CDU) described the nationwide demonstrations against right-wing extremism with thousands of participants as encouraging. &quot;The &apos;silent&apos; majority is raising its voice and showing that it wants to live in a country that is open to the world and free.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>North Rhine-Westphalia State Premier</strong></p>
<p>North Rhine-Westphalia State Premier Hendrik Wüst said: &quot;These days, tens of thousands of people throughout our region are showing civil courage. They are raising their voices in Cologne, Duisburg, Dortmund, Essen and many other cities and demonstrating peacefully against racism and right-wing extremism - and thus in favour of a Germany that is open to the world.&quot; &quot;They are all urgently demonstrating that there is no place for arsonists and agitators in our country. Thank you for this important sign of democracy.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>International Auschwitz Committee</strong></p>
<p>The International Auschwitz Committee thanked the people who protested across Germany. &quot;Holocaust survivors are more than grateful to all those who are taking to the streets these days against the hatred and lies of the far-right. They see these demonstrations as a powerful sign from the citizens and a revitalisation of democracy that they have long hoped and waited for,&quot; said Executive Vice President Christoph Heubner.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayors from large cities and small towns</strong></p>
<p>The city mayors of large German metropolises, the mayors of hundreds of small and medium-sized towns and the leaders of rural communities (Landräte) gave the nationwide protests their strongest support. Not only did the municipalities make it possible for the protests to take place undisturbed and peacefully, but the mayors were proud of and grateful for the commitment of their fellow citizens.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>German Association of Towns and Cities</strong></p>
<p>The Association of German Towns and Cities (Deutscher Städtetag) wrote in a declaration (Trier Deklaration) that human dignity, democracy and the rule of law must be defended repeatedly. &quot;The recently publicised meeting between AfD functionaries and members of the Identitarian movement and the deportation of millions of people from Germany discussed there has shocked us all. We will not accept that right-wing extremist forces are fuelling an atmosphere of uncertainty, fear and hatred in our country and our cities.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“People from different backgrounds live together in our cities - as neighbours, as colleagues, as friends, as family. This is the reality of life in our urban societies. That is what makes our cities special. Our cities belong to all the people who live here. We do not accept that citizens, families and even children in our cities must be afraid of being driven out.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayor of Munich</strong></p>
<p>In the Bavarian capital, Mayor Dieter Reiter was &quot;overwhelmed by the sign that the people of Munich have set in favour of democracy and against racism, anti-Semitism and right-wing agitation.&quot; He continued: &quot;These are the moments when I am proud to be the Mayor of Munich: “When hundreds of thousands of people are here to speak out against hate and discrimination, against a political shift to the right in Germany, in Bavaria, but also in Munich.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayor of Hamburg</strong></p>
<p>In Hamburg, Mayor Peter Tschentscher took part in the demonstration against right-wing extremism and neo-Nazi networks. He explained: &quot;Hamburg is a cosmopolitan city. A city of tolerance. Everyone is welcome here, including those seeking protection. There is no place for racism here.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayor of Leipzig</strong></p>
<p>In Leipzig, city councillors joined in the protest against right-wing extremism. During the rally, Mayor Burkhard Jung spoke to the demonstrators. The Mayor read out racist quotes from AfD politicians and commented: &quot;I can&apos;t think of anything to say about this except: it makes me want to vomit!&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Young mayors of Germany</strong></p>
<p>More than 100 young German mayors signed a declaration against far-right extremism</p>
<p>“As young mayors, we stand together for the values of diversity, tolerance and respectful coexistence. We are concerned about the deportation plans of right-wing extremist activists centred around the AfD, which aim to discriminate against and expel people based on their origin.”</p>
<p><span style="color: black;"> </span></p>
<p>“Our cities and communities are places of diversity and cohesion, where people of different backgrounds and beliefs live and work together. This diversity makes us strong and resilient in the face of extremist endeavours. In recent days, numerous demonstrations for cohesion and democracy in many cities have shown that we are a resilient democracy.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayors from the Münsterland region (North Rhine-Westphalia)</strong></p>
<p>Mayors from the Münsterland region are protesting against right-wing extremism in a joint initiative.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;We are worried about the continued existence of democracy,&quot; says Jörn Möltgen, Mayor of Havixbeck and initiator of the protest, summarising the reason for the action. In discussions with colleagues from the region, it was spontaneously decided: &quot;We are in favour of diversity, tolerance and respectful coexistence. Who else, if not us?&quot; says the Green politician. 14 mayors have spontaneously united to protest and want to gather behind a banner with the words &quot;Mayors against right-wing extremism and in favour of democracy&quot; at an anti-AfD demonstration. Among those taking part are Coesfeld Mayor Eliza Diekmann, Katrin Rauscher from Sendenhorst and Karl Piochowiak from Ostbevern. Münster&apos;s Mayor Markus Lewe will also be joining the protests.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayors from Baden-Württemberg</strong></p>
<p>Dozens of city mayors from Baden-Württemberg have joined forces against right-wing groups in politics and called for protests. Right-wing extremist movements are attempting to undermine the basic democratic order in Germany, according to a statement by 30 mayors from the region. Everyone is now called upon to speak out in favour of a democratic future for the country. &quot;This means responsibility for all of us,&quot; the mayors appealed, calling for a &quot;solidarity of the democratic centre&quot;.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Mayors from the Stuttgart region</strong></p>
<p>Local politicians from the Stuttgart region called for a &quot;solidarity of the democratic centre&quot; for democracy and against right-wing extremism. &quot;We are very concerned about the current developments in our society: “Right-wing extremist movements are trying to undermine our basic democratic order,&quot; reads an open letter from 30 mayors. The first signatories include Frank Nopper from Stuttgart, Boris Palmer from Tübingen, Matthias Knecht from Ludwigsburg, Carmen Haberstroh from Metzingen and Matthias Klopfer from Esslingen, who initiated the campaign.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>PLEASE SUGGEST:</strong> Please <u><a href="german.brief.org@gmail.com" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">suggest</a></u> a mayor who has spoken out against the far-right. Please provide the town, city or village, the federal state and his/her name together with some information.</p>
<p><em>Bitte schlagen Sie einen Bürgermeister vor, der sich gegen Rechtsextremismus ausgesprochen hat. Bitte geben Sie die Stadt, den Ort, das Bundesland und seinen/ihren Namen zusammen mit einigen Informationen an. </em><u><em><a href="german.brief.org@gmail.com" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Email</a></em></u></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/margot-friedlander-holocaust-survivor" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Margot Friedländer - Holocaust survivor</a></strong><strong> | </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/business-against-far-right" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German business against the far-right</a></strong><strong> |  </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-constitution" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">75 years German post-war constitution</a></strong><strong> |  </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</a></strong><strong> | </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer">Anti far-right demos in Berlin and hundreds of other German towns and cities</a></strong><strong>  |  </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Descendants of German Nazi resistance fighters  against the far-right</a></strong><strong> || </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German mayor against the far-right</a></strong><strong> | </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/rainbow-flag-pirna" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Protestant church flies rainbow flag in defiance of right-wing mayor</a></span></strong><strong> |</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Please comment</a></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong><a href="#9tqlb" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nazi resistance fighters]]></title><description><![CDATA[Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to their fellow citizens to reject the New Right]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters</link><guid isPermaLink="false">65c263d8c84c87cf74b34f3f</guid><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 17:24:51 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">Descendants of German resistance fighters appeal to their fellow citizens to reject the New Right</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_26c03b3396fc4b38a587b4656f80d19d~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_ef69c9b17477470ca41c983c3b2ceb12~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_1708a44a82be4f1086e5aa680f2090ac~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p>German Nazi resistance fighters (left to right): Descendants of Carl Friedrich Goerdeler, Claus Schenk Graf von Stauffenberg and Dietrich Bonhoeffer were among those who called for a rejection of Germany&apos;s New Right.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>February 2024:</strong> More than 280 descendants and relatives of Nazi resistance fighters have appealed to voters in Germany in an open letter. They call on people to learn from Germany&apos;s history and to stand up to the New Right. In their open letter below, they write that it was their parents, grandparents and great-grandparents who stood up to Nazi atrocities as resistance fighters.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>&quot;That is why we, as relatives and descendants, are speaking out and calling on all fellow citizens to stand up to the New Right in our country and across Europe.&quot; Everyone should feel responsible for preserving and defending liberal democracy and the rule of law.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The letter entitled &quot;Learning from history, strengthening democracy!&quot; was signed by more than 280 men and women, including the descendants of Dietrich Bonhoeffer, Claus Schenk Graf von Stauffenberg and Carl Friedrich Goerdeler. (<span style="color: #ae5050;"><a href="https://stiftung-adam-von-trott.de/die-stiftung/blog-details?tx_news_pi1%5Baction%5D=detail&tx_news_pi1%5Bcontroller%5D=News&tx_news_pi1%5Bnews%5D=421&cHash=4518a3c82f536683d0d3e0c243e35b39" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Full list of signatories</a></span>)</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Dear fellow citizens</strong></p>
<p><em>(Original German text below)</em></p>
<p>Dissatisfaction, pessimism, fear of the future: Populists and enemies of democracy are gaining support in many countries. They stir up fears: of social decline, of foreigners, of everything new. They stir up mistrust and hatred: of the media, of the government, of elites, of minorities, of anyone different.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>People are particularly susceptible to this in times of crisis. In Germany, we have already experienced where this can lead. It was our parents, grandparents and great-grandparents who stood up to Nazi injustice as resistance fighters. That is why we, as relatives and descendants, are speaking out today and calling on all our fellow citizens to stand up to the <em>New Right</em> in our country and throughout Europe. We should all feel responsible for preserving and defending liberal democracy and the rule of law.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Most people in our country have learned from the catastrophe of the Nazi dictatorship. But many have forgotten how quickly disappointment and a lack of prospects can lead to temptation. When even members of the Bundestag are talking about the ‘remigration’ of millions of people when right-wing extremist parties are leading the polls in several east German states and democratic parties are wavering helplessly between ingratiation, delimiting arrogance and fantasies of banning the right, then alarm bells must be ringing for all supporters of an open society.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Democratic structures and institutions can collapse if citizens do not stand behind them and help to preserve them. We need greater commitment from democrats. It is therefore an encouraging sign that more and more people are taking to the streets and getting involved against the right since the publications by the media house ‘Correctiv’ about the plans of right-wing extremists.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>But demonstrations alone are not enough. It is even more important to vote. In the European elections on 9 June this year, there are fears that right-wing parties in particular could be among the winners in Europe due to low turnout. We are concerned that the democratic parties have not campaigned enough so far.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The far-right AfD party (Alternative for Germany) must not win in this autumn’s state elections in Brandenburg, Thuringia and Saxony. Our voice as democrats is needed here, as well as political debate with friends, acquaintances, colleagues and in the media. We are convinced that there can be a good future - if we manage to work on it together. Let us learn from history and strengthen democracy!</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Liebe Mitbürger</strong></p>
<p>Unzufriedenheit, Pessimismus, Zukunftsangst: In vielen Ländern gewinnen Populisten und Feinde der Demokratie an Zustimmung. Sie schüren Ängste: vor sozialem Abstieg, vor Fremden, vor allem Neuen. Sie schüren Misstrauen und Hass: auf die Medien, auf die Regierung, auf „Eliten“, auf Minderheiten, auf alle, die „anders“ sind.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In Krisenzeiten sind Menschen dafür besonders empfänglich. Wir haben in Deutschland schon einmal erlebt, wohin das führen kann. Es waren unsere Eltern, Großeltern und Urgroßeltern, die sich dem NS-Unrecht damals als Widerstandskämpfer entgegengestellt haben. Deshalb melden wir uns als Angehörige und Nachkommen heute zu Wort und fordern alle Mitbürger dazu auf, der Neuen Rechte in unserem Land und europaweit die Stirn zu bieten. Wir sollten uns alle dafür verantwortlich fühlen, die liberale und rechtsstaatliche Demokratie zu bewahren und sie zu verteidigen.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Die meisten Menschen in unserem Land haben aus der Katastrophe der NS-Diktatur gelernt. Aber viele haben vergessen, wie schnell Enttäuschung und Perspektivlosigkeit verführbar machen. Wenn selbst Bundestagsabgeordnete von millionenfacher „Remigration“ sprechen, wenn rechtsextreme Parteien in mehreren Bundesländern die Umfragen anführen und demokratische Parteien hilflos zwischen Anbiederung, abgrenzender Arroganz und Verbotsfantasien schwanken, dann müssen bei allen Anhängern der offenen Gesellschaft die Alarmglocken schrillen. Demokratische Strukturen und Institutionen können zusammenbrechen, wenn die Bürger nicht hinter ihnen stehen und sie bewahren helfen. Wir brauchen ein stärkeres Engagement der Demokratinnen und Demokraten.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Es ist deshalb ein ermutigendes Zeichen, wenn seit den Veröffentlichungen des Medienhauses &quot;Correctiv&quot; über die Pläne von Rechtsextremisten immer mehr Menschen auf die Straße gehen und sich „gegen rechts“ engagieren. Aber Demonstrationen allein reichen nicht aus. Noch wichtiger ist es, wählen zu gehen. Bei der Europawahl am 9. Juni steht aufgrund zu niedriger Beteiligung zu befürchten, dass vor allem rechte Parteien zu den Gewinnern in Europa zählen könnten. Mit Sorge beobachten wir, dass die demokratischen Parteien bisher zu wenig Wahlkampf betreiben.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Auch die Landtagswahlen in Brandenburg, Thüringen und Sachsen dürfen nicht zugunsten der AfD ausgehen. Da ist unsere Stimme als Demokraten gefragt, aber auch die politische Debatte mit Freunden, Bekannten, Kollegen und in den Medien. Wir sind überzeugt, dass es eine gute Zukunft geben kann – wenn wir es schaffen, gemeinsam daran zu arbeiten. Lasst uns aus der Geschichte lernen und die Demokratie stärken! (<span style="color: #ae5050;"><a href="https://stiftung-adam-von-trott.de/die-stiftung/blog-details?tx_news_pi1%5Baction%5D=detail&tx_news_pi1%5Bcontroller%5D=News&tx_news_pi1%5Bnews%5D=421&cHash=4518a3c82f536683d0d3e0c243e35b39" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Vollständige Liste der Unterzeichner</a></span>)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/margot-friedlander-holocaust-survivor" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Margot Friedländer - Holocaust survivor</a></strong><strong> |  </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-constitution" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">75 years Germany&apos;s post-war constitution</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer">Anti far-right demos in Berlin and hundreds of other German towns and cities</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;">  | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Descendants of German Nazi resistance fighters  against the far-right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German mayor against the far-right</a></span></strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"> | </span></strong><strong> </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/rainbow-flag-pirna" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">Protestant church flies rainbow flag in defiance of right-wing mayor</a></span></strong><strong> </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;">|</span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><strong><span style="color: #d21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Please comment</a></span></strong></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[World Mayor Awards]]></title><description><![CDATA[Stefan Fassbinder, the Mayor of Greifswald, Germany wins the 2023 World Mayor Friendship Award]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/world-mayor-awards</link><guid isPermaLink="false">65be52aa56f183c1c1414e7e</guid><category><![CDATA[Towns & Cities]]></category><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 15:19:27 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">WORLD MAYOR 2023</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Stefan Fassbinder, Mayor of Greifswald, Germany, given the World Mayor Friendship Award</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_3d24267c3f8b4b0b94c3bc180bbf3951~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Stefan Fassbinder wins the 2023 World Mayor Friendship Award"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: black;"><strong>February 2024:</strong></span><span style="color: black;"> The London-based City Mayors Foundation has announced the winners of the </span><a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/index.html" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>2023 World Mayor Prize and Awards</strong></span></a><span style="color: black;">. The biennial honours have been awarded since 2004.</span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>The 2023 <a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/winners-2023/stefan-fassbinder-greifswald.html" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>World Mayor Friendship Award</strong></span></a> has been given to Stefan Fassbinder, Mayor of Greifswald, Germany, for his and the city’s cooperation with and support of communities in Ukraine, Poland and Brazil. He, together with many of his fellow citizens, has also provided generous assistance to refugees arriving from war-torn Ukraine.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Tann vom Hove, Senior Fellow of the City Mayors Foundation, described Stefan Fassbinder as a mayor who understood the importance of towns and cities working together. At a time of strife in many regions of the world, cities, when cooperating, can facilitate peaceful solutions.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In his essay for the World Mayor Project, Mayor Fassbinder wrote: “Through city-to-city relationships, peace can be promoted. Cultural exchange and dialogue help break down misunderstandings and promote peaceful coexistence. In difficult times, municipalities can often still engage in dialogue when others resort to violence. Greifswald embraces this opportunity and responsibility of cities.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Tann vom Hove praised Mayor Fassbinder but also the people of Greifswald for their willingness to share expertise and resources with less fortunate communities.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The World Mayor Friendship Award was conceived to promote cooperation between towns and cities in Europe and beyond.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Stefan Fassbinder will be presented with the World Mayor Friendship Plaque.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In addition to the Friendship Award, the City Mayors Foundation has given the 2023 World Mayor Prize, the 2023 Jury Award and the 2023 Partnership Award.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/winners-2023/elke-kahr-graz.html" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>The 2023 World Mayor Prize</strong></span></a> was awarded to <span style="color: black;">Elke Kahr, Mayor of Graz, Austria for her selfless dedication to her city and its people. For Mayor Kahr politics means serving her fellow citizens with humility. Her decision to share a large part of her salary with people in need has attracted worldwide admiration.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/winners-2023/manuel-de-araujo-quelimone.html" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>The World Mayor Jury Award</strong></span></a> was conferred on Manuel De Araújo, Mayor of Quelimane, Mozambique, for his defence of democratic values in his country and his ambitious plans and initiatives to make Quelimane one of the most sustainable cities in Africa.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="http://www.worldmayor.com/winners-2023/tony-keats-dover.html" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>The World Mayor Community Award</strong></span></a> was conferred on Tony Keats, Mayor of Dover, Canada, for his dedicated service to the Town of Dover and his fellow citizens since 1996. Tony Keats has also been commended for his willingness to share his knowledge and expertise with other communities in the province of Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada and even South America.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank"><span style="color: #ed5829;"><strong>Please comment</strong></span></a></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Demos against hate]]></title><description><![CDATA[Germans against the far-right From the Coasts to the Alps, Germans are protesting against the far-right: "Menschenrechte statt rechte...]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate</link><guid isPermaLink="false">65abea9f54dc4bee75c9d2cb</guid><category><![CDATA[Society]]></category><category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 16:23:01 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Germans against the far-right</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>From the Coasts to the Alps, Germans are protesting against the far-right: </strong><em><strong>&quot;Menschenrechte statt rechte Menschen&quot;</strong></em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_41b7a4e0a950484c87cf67056f27cc33~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p>March 2024: In Saarland, Germany&apos;s smallest state, old and young took to the streets in citieds and small towns against the right</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Germany’s smallest state confronts the right</strong></p>
<p><strong>March 2024:</strong> In recent weeks and days in Saarland, Germany’s smallest state after the city-states of Berlin, Hamburg and Bremen, tens of thousands of people demonstrated against the right and its ideology of racism, xenophobia and hate.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Across the state, which is home to less than one million people, protests took place in the state capital Saarbrücken and many smaller towns including Neunkirchen, St Wendel and St Ingbert. On Sunday, 17 March, around 3,000 people took to the streets in Saarbrücken to protest against right-wing extremism. They marched through the city centre. Everything went peacefully, said a police spokesman in Saarbrücken. An alliance called ‘Against the AfD and racism’, which is supported by around 20 groups, had called for the action. <em>(The AfD or Alternative für Deutschland, is the country’s principal far-right party.)</em></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Anti-right protests also took place in rural areas of Saarland. Around 250 demonstrators gathered on the market square in Wadern for a protest on Saturday afternoon (16 March). They stood up for an open society. Under the motto &quot;The Hochwald remains colourful&quot;, protesters followed the call of a broad alliance of local organisations in the rural Hochwald district.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The organisers, which included an alliance of church communities, saw the rally on Saturday as a prelude to similar actions that are to take place in other rural districts over the coming weekends. The aim is to stand together against the shift to the right in politics and society.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Separately, Saarland’s business associations and trade unions issued a rare joint statement, warning against the rise of right-wing extremism. “The far right is damaging the local economy and will make Saarland less attractive to investors. Existing jobs will be lost, new ones not created.”</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Small-town Germany speaks out against the far-right</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>February, 2024:</strong> While on the previous two weekends, hundreds of thousands of Germans took to the streets to oppose the ideology (Gedankengut) of far-right groups or parties, including the AfD (Alternative für Deutschland / Alternative for Germany) in large cities like Berlin, Hamburg or Stuttgart, this weekend (10/11 February) protests and demonstrations took place in smaller towns.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the police, up to 4,000 people demonstrated in Itzehoe (Popl 33,000) In Rostock (Popl 209,000), some 4,000 people gathered under the slogan ‘Never again is now’ (Nie wieder ist jetzt). There were around 2,000 in Werne (Popl 30,000) and around 1,200 in Fröndenberg (Popl 22,000). ‘Sinsheim is colourful!’ (Sinsheim ist bunt) was the motto under which around 1,500 people gathered in the town (Popl 35,000) in Baden-Württemberg.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>In Gotha (Popl 45,000), Thurin dgia, the slogan also was ‘Never again is now’. A representative of the Gotha-is-colourful alliance spoke of at least 1,100 participants.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>There were also various rallies in other German towns. with several hundred participants, for example in Timmendorfer Strand (Popl 9,000) and Herford (Popl 67,000). In Ennepetal (Popl 30,000) in the southern Ruhr region, around 900 people gathered under the slogan ‘Ennepetal against the AfD’. &quot;Democracy is an achievement. It cannot be taken for granted and it is not inviolable. We must defend it,&quot; the organisers said.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>-------------------------</strong></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>February 2024:</strong> Once again this weekend (3/4 February), hundreds of thousands of Germans demonstrated against the far-right. In Berlin alone, 200,000 people gathered in front of the Reichstag building (German parliament).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Under the slogan <em>‘We are the firewall: Alliance against the right&quot; (</em><em><span style="color: rgb(51, 50, 47);">Wir sind die Brandmauer: Bündnis gegen rechts)</span></em>’, men, women, the old and the young protested in Berlin against right-wing extremism and the far-right AfD party (Alternative for Germany / Alternative für Deutschland).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The rally was called by the alliance &quot;Hand in Hand - Act in Solidarity Now!&quot; Tens of thousands of people joined hands and raised their hands to the sky. The event was directed against right-wing extremism and called for &quot;the defence of an open and democratic society&quot;. Political parties were not among the organisers, but many politicians took part in the rally.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Demonstrations also took place in numerous other cities. According to the police, almost 25,000 people gathered in Augsburg (Bavaria). The crowds were so large that the town hall square was cordoned off. The adjacent streets were then cleared for the demonstration so that the large number of people could disperse.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the police, around 30,000 people gathered in Freiburg to protest against right-wing extremism. More than 300 organisations, including the Bundesliga soccer club SC Freiburg, trade unions and churches, had called for the largest event in the state of Baden-Württemberg. Similar protests were also registered elsewhere in Baden-Wüerttemberg, in Lahr, Lörrach, Wiesloch and Aalen.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>According to the police, more than 7,000 people peacefully formed a dense human chain around the Lower Saxony state parliament in Hannover. The organisers spoke of around 10,000 participants. Signs and posters bore slogans such as &quot;Human rights instead of right-wing humans&quot; (it sounds better in German: Menschenrechte statt rechte Menschen.)</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Thousands of people also took to the streets in Dresden. A rally was initially held on Theaterplatz (theatre square), followed by a demonstration march through the old town. More than 200 organisations, institutions and initiatives from Saxony had called for a demonstration under the slogan ‘We are the firewall’. &quot;There were 30,000 of us today,&quot; said a spokeswoman for the alliance.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Protests also took place in many other cities. According to the police, up to 10,000 people gathered in Krefeld and Mainz. According to the organisers, more than 15,000 people took part in Saarbrücken.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>German Chancellor Olaf Scholz described the demonstrations as a &quot;strong sign&quot; for democracy and the Basic Law (German constitution). &quot;Whether in Eisenach, Homburg or Berlin: in small and large cities across the country, many citizens are coming together to demonstrate against forgetting, against hatred and agitation - this weekend too,&quot; the Scholz wrote. The Chancellor himself took part in a rally in Potsdam in January.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The leader of the far-right AfD, Tino Chrupalla, described the numerous rallies in the country as a distraction by the government. In an interview he said: &quot;Of course, the government is currently using the demonstrations in order to distract attention from the real problems.&quot;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
-------------------------------</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>January 2024:</strong> Factory workers, mayors, AI programmers, teachers, taxi drivers, sex workers pensioners, college students, rappers, footballers, doctors, and industry bosses are among hundreds of thousands of Germans who have been and will be demonstrating against right-wing extremism. At least 80,000 people in Hamburg and Munich, 100,000 people in Berlin, 20,000 people in Karlsruhe and Stuttgart, at least 10,000 people in Leipzig and up to 40,000 people in Dresden. According to police reports, hundreds of thousands of people took to the streets throughout Germany at the weekend to protest against right-wing extremism and for democracy. The organizers even estimate that a total of 1.4 million people took part in the demonstrations on Friday, Saturday and Sunday. (19 to 21 January 2024)</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>Background</strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>The background to the current wave of protests against right-wing extremism in Germany is a meeting between far-right propagandists and politicians from the AfD (Alternative for Germany) and the rightist wing of Germany’s main opposition party the CDU (Christian Democratic Union) in a villa in Potsdam, south of Berlin.</strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong> </strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>The media outlet Correctiv made the Potsdam meeting public. The central point of the meeting was that the former head of the right-wing extremist Identarian Movement in Austria, Martin Sellner, spoke about ‘re-migration’. When right-wing extremists use the term, they usually mean that a large number of people of foreign origin should leave the country - even under duress. AfD politicians also use the term.</strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong> </strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>Martin Sellner’s idea of re-migration seemed to be the focal point of the gathering. Everything else – Covid restrictions and vaccinations, the issues of Ukraine and Israel – are all bones of contention on the right. Their stance on re-migration, however, is what unites them.</strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong> </strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>The Sellner masterplan even includes a destination to ‘move people to’, a so-called ‘model state’ in North Africa, that would apparently provide space for up to two million people. Sellner’s concept is eerily reminiscent of the Nazi’s 1940 plan to deport four million Jews to the island of Madagascar. It is unclear whether Sellner had this historical parallel in mind when devising his plan. It may also be a mere coincidence that the organisers of the event chose a location less than eight kilometres away from the villa where the 1942 Wannsee Conference took place, the meeting where the Nazis coordinated the systematic extermination of Jews.</strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong> </strong></span></em></p>
<p><em><span style="color: #5b093e;"><strong>With only ten months to go until the regional elections in the German states of Thuringia, Saxony and Brandenburg, this meeting has shown that racist attitudes extend into the highest echelons of the AfD party. And it doesn’t stop with attitudes; certain politicians want to put their racist ideas into action, despite the fact the AfD firmly denies that it is a right-wing extremist party.</strong></span></em></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>Demos and protests</strong></p>
<p>Around 3,300 people demonstrated against right-wing extremism and the AfD in Jena, Thuringia. The state in eastern Germany, once home to leading liberal writers and philosophers like Friedrich von Schiller, Alexander von Humboldt and Wilhelm Hegel, has recently become a stronghold of the far-right Alternative for Germany party (Alternative für Deutschland, AfD).</p>
<p> </p>
<p>At the demonstration, Thuringia&apos;s socialist Prime Minister Bodo Ramelow called for unity against the right. He described the people on the streets as a firewall. He pointed out that large companies in the state, such as Jenoptik, needed to be open to the world. Ramelow said that there should not be the impression that some of the people who live here are no longer welcome.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Earlier in the week, some 10,000 people in Freiburg, southwestern Germany, filled the historic city centre to call for an end to antisemitism, islamophobia and xenophobia of any kind. One of the thousands demonstrating against right-wing extremism in Freiburg was Christian Streich, the manager of Bundesliga club SC Freiburg.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Football against the far-right</strong></p>
<p>In a remarkable speech, <u><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/christian-streich-freiburg" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #000000;">Christian Streich</span></a></u>, the manager of Bundesliga club SC Freiburg, called out for Germans to end their complacency. “It&apos;s five to twelve,&quot; he said. &quot;Everyone in this country is called upon to take a clear stance in the family, at work or elsewhere. Those who remain seated now or claim that AfD voters are protest voters cannot complain afterwards if they are governed by a right-wing populist group and lose the liberal rights they have worked hard for since 1945.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“I have been living in a democracy for 58 years. That is incredibly lucky.” The Freiburg football manager also quoted 102-year-old Margo Friedländer, a Holocaust survivor, who said in a speech in the German federal parliament (Bundestag) that the current situation in the country reminded her of the Weimar Republic and its consequences.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Christian Streich was not the only one from the world of football to call for protests against the right. FC Köln (Cologne) defender Timo Hübers praised a demonstration against the right in the Bundesliga club&apos;s home city and took a clear stance against right-wing ideas. The Bundesliga club VfB Stuttgart put out a statement saying that it stood &quot;for our free and democratic society, for peaceful coexistence and openness to the world.” Schalke 04 announced several days of action for diversity and tolerance over the next two weeks to send a clear signal against hatred and hate speech. &quot;It is very important for us, especially in the current times, to stand up as Schalke players,&quot; said CEO Matthias Tillmann.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> <strong>Politics, businesses and churches support the protests</strong></p>
<p>Away from the world of football, representatives from politics, business and the churches condemned right-wing extremism and called on Germans from the centre of society to join the protests.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The President of the Central Council of Jews in Germany (Zentralrat der Juden), Josef Schuster, described the demonstrations as an &quot;important signal&quot;. &quot;I am pleased that the centre of society is standing up,&quot; Schuster told the <em>Augsburger Allgemeine</em> newspaper. “I’ve always been worried about people&apos;s complacency despite the AfD’s popularity in the polls. That&apos;s why I&apos;m delighted when people now take to the streets and express their fury.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>German Chancellor (Bundeskanzler) Olaf Scholz also backed the demonstrators. In a video address, he said that all people in Germany were called upon to take an unequivocal stand for tolerance, cohesion and democracy. He compared the plans of right-wing extremists to the racial ideology of the National Socialists. &quot;If anything must never again have a place in Germany, then it is the Germanic racial ideology of the National Socialists.&quot;</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>German mayors against the far-right</strong></p>
<p>More than 100 young German mayors signed a declaration against far-right extremism</p>
<p>“As young mayors, we stand together for the values of diversity, tolerance and respectful coexistence. We are concerned about the deportation plans of right-wing extremist activists centred around the AfD, which aim to discriminate against and expel people based on their origin.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“We are living in times of many challenges, which also give rise to fears. We read with disgust that people are meeting to seriously discuss a plan to seriously discuss a plan to expel people from our country. It was probably not the first meeting of this kind and it will not be the last.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“Unfortunately, these people are not isolated. They are networked in parliaments,</p>
<p>parties, associations and companies - from the extreme right to the centre of society.</p>
<p>centre of society.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p>“Our cities and communities are places of diversity and cohesion, where people of different backgrounds and beliefs live and work together. This diversity makes us strong and resilient in the face of extremist endeavours. In recent days, numerous demonstrations for cohesion and democracy in many cities have shown that we are a resilient democracy.”</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>ON OTHER PAGES: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/business-against-far-right" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>German business against the far-right</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> |  </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/anti-semitic-crimes" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Extremist politics at the root of anti-Semitism</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/demos-against-hate" rel="noreferrer"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Anti far-right demos in Berlin and hundreds of other German towns and cities</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>  </strong></span><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>| </strong></span><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/nazi-resistance-fighters" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Descendants of German Nazi resistance fighters  against the far-right</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> | </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/buergermeister-gegen-rechts" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>German mayor against the far-right</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> |  </strong></span><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/rainbow-flag-pirna" rel="noreferrer" target="_top"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Protestant church flies rainbow flag in defiance of right-wing mayor</strong></span></a><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong> |</strong></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>IN YOUR OPINION: </strong><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank"><span style="color: #d21111;"><strong>Please comment</strong></span></a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong><a href="#lo6d215335" rel="noopener noreferrer">BACK TO TOP</a></strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Martin Walser]]></title><description><![CDATA[Marint Walser wrote for and about ordinary people]]></description><link>https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/martin-walser</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6534146109feadc2138433c6</guid><category><![CDATA[The Arts]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 18:29:48 GMT</pubDate><dc:creator>German Brief</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">GERMAN BOOKS</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Martin Walser wrote for</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">and about ordinary people</p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/393075_1e0e7a821931498e97c88b08601a2156~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_300,h_300,al_c,q_80/file.png"alt="Martin Walser"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><strong>July 2023: </strong>The German journalist Wolfgang A Peters described his friend Martin Walser not only as one of the greatest German writers of the 20th century but also one who wrote like no other about and for ordinary people in post-war Germany. Now Martin Walser is dead. He died on 28 July 2023, in Überlingen on Lake Constance, less than 100 kilometres from his birthplace of Wasserburg.

Martin Walser was one of the greats who shaped German literature after World War II. Although he never received the same international recognition as Günter Grass (The Tin Drum) or Heinrich Böll (Group Portrait with Lady), many of his books were translated into English and other languages.

Walser&apos;s best internationally known works are probably: Tod eines Kritikers (Death of a Critic), Ein fliehendes Pferd (A Runaway Horse) and Ehen in Philippsburg (Marriage in Philippsburg).

<em>Marriage in Philippsburg</em>:
<em>This is really strong stuff, what Martin Walser slammed in the face of the bourgeois post-war society with his first novel in 1957. That the profiteers of the ‘economic miracle’ rejected the novel is not surprising. Those who are unsparingly held up to the mirror are offended when they learn the truth about themselves and their peers! Walser&apos;s episodic narrative style, with its uncanny linguistic force, is for me a document of the times that, in addition to the plot, fully convinced me literarily. (Review by Habicht)</em>

In total, Walser wrote more than 70 books and countless stories and essays. At times, readers could count on a new title from him every year.

Along with the Peace Prize of the German Book Trade, the renowned Georg Büchner Prize (1981) and the international Friedrich Nietzsche Prize (2015), which he received for his life&apos;s work, were among Walser&apos;s most notable awards. Even though he perhaps hoped for more international recognition, Walser could always count on his numerous readers, who enjoyed his novels featuring broken heroes.

Martin Walser’s acceptance speech for the Peace Prize of the German Book Trade in 1998 led to controversy. He had criticised the fact that Germans were confronted with &quot;a never-ending shame,&quot; he said, referring to the atrocities committed by the Nazis. &quot;But when every day in the media this past is presented to me, I notice that something inside me is opposing this permanent show of our shame,&quot; he added. The Peace Prize winner saw in the &quot;celebration of shame&quot; the risk of turning remembrance of the Holocaust into a &quot;lip service&quot; ritual.

Walser disliked literary critics, especially those who did not appreciate his work. Among them was Marcel Reich-Ranicki, the literary editor at the Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung (FAZ) newspaper, who “recognised the author&apos;s diligence but criticised his lack of imagination.” Walser attempted to settle accounts with his 2002 novel, Tod eines Kritikers (Death of a Critic). However, that backfired, as the author was accused of anti-Semitism in his depiction of the critic.

Germany&apos;s President Frank-Walter Steinmeier wrote to Walser&apos;s widow Käthe: &quot;We will never forget him and will always read him.&quot;

&quot;If one were to name an example of historically conscious, committed poetry in post-war German literature, who else would come to mind first but Martin Walser?&quot; the Federal President wrote. &quot;With his books and essays, Walser opened many people&apos;s eyes, above all, about the country they live in and about the times they live in. We all mourn Martin Walser. We will not forget him and always read him.&quot;

&quot;Martin Walser was not only one of the most important German writers, he was also a first-rate contemporary witness to the development of the German Federal Republic in the post-war period and in the reunified Germany,&quot; said Petra Olschowski, Baden-Württemberg&apos;s Minister of the Arts. &quot;With his literary work and his contributions to the overall social debate, she said, he himself had written contemporary history.&quot;

Walser was born on 24 March 1927 in Wasserburg on Lake Constance and died on 28 July in Überlingen, also on Lake Constance. The last volume of his poems was published in spring 2023 under the title &quot;Fisch und Vogel lassen grüßen&quot;.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>On other pages: <span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/books" target="_blank">Books</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/opera" target="_blank">Opera</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/german-cinema" target="_blank">Cinema</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/hertha-gordon-walcher" target="_top">Hertha Gordon- Walcher</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> | </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/pages/german-book-prize-2024" rel="noreferrer" target="_top">German Book Prize 2024</a></span><span style="color: #D21111;"> |</span></p>
<p>In your opinion:<span style="color: #D21111;"> </span><span style="color: #D21111;"><a href="https://www.germanbrief.com/comments" target="_blank">Please comment</a></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>